<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great duty of Christians to go forth without the camp to Jesus set forth in several sermons on Heb. XIII. 13 / by S.T.M. ...</title>
            <author>Tomlyns, Samuel, 1632 or 3-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1860</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2505</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12129770</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12129770</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54706</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62909)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54706)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 900:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great duty of Christians to go forth without the camp to Jesus set forth in several sermons on Heb. XIII. 13 / by S.T.M. ...</title>
                  <author>Tomlyns, Samuel, 1632 or 3-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst, ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews XIII, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54706:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54706:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> GREAT DUTY OF <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> TO <hi>Go forth without the Camp.</hi> TO JESUS: Set forth in ſeveral SERMONS On <hi>Hebr.</hi> XIII. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> S. T. <hi>M. of A. of</hi> Trinity-<hi>College in</hi> Cambridge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Three Bibles and Crown</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:54706:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54706:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>WILLIAM</hi> Lord <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SSEL,</hi> Grace, Mercy, and Peace be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied, from God our Father, and from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is one of the wonderful Riddles, and deep Myſteries of Providence, That the Church, that hath the leaſt of Sin, ſhould yet endure the moſt of Sufferings; That the Metal that is beſt refined, ſhould be most often caſt into the Furnace; and, That they that are moſt white in their Souls with the Beauty of Holineſs, ſhould be ſo black'd in their Outward Man and State by the ſcorching Sun of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. How hard is it for thoſe that live by Senſe, to believe, That they ſhall wear glittering Crowns, and ſit on glorious Thrones for ever, that now are cruſhed as Worms under the Feet of Sinners, and are
<pb facs="tcp:54706:3"/>bruiſed as Grapes in the Wine-preſs of the Worlds Rage and Fury? But as the Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born of God's New Family veiled his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, emptied himſelf, and hid his Glory, <hi>Phil. 2.6. His viſage was marred more than any man, and his form than the ſons of men, Iſa. 52.14.</hi> ſo his younger Brethren are arraied in dark Parables of Shame, Reproach, and Sufferings. The bleſſed Life of Saints is now hidden, and a baſe and courſe Covering is ſpread over all their intrinſick Glory; they are (as it were) diſguiſed and <hi>incognitol</hi> in the World, <hi>1 John 3.1. Pignorius</hi> obſerves, <hi>Quicquid Taetrum, Saevum, Horribile in Chriſtianos olim excogitatum, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitum eſt, illud omne (ut ego Cenſeo) a ſervis ad illos tranſivit,</hi> De Servis, p. <hi>9.</hi> That is, <hi>Whatſoever Grievous, Horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and Cruel Torments were of old practiſed againſt the Chriſtians in the Primitive Times, were juſt the ſame that cruel Maſters uſed to inflict on their bought Slaves.</hi> O what a dark Veil was caſt over the Adopted Sons of God, when they were treated juſt as imperious and tyrannical Maſters uſed to handle their poor and vile Slaves! Thoſe that the World
<pb facs="tcp:54706:3"/>hath not been worthy of, have been driven Into Wilderneſſes, as if they were not worthy to converſe with, and live among Men: <hi>The precious Sons of</hi> Zion, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to fine Gold,</hi> have been reputed as the <hi>vile potſheards of the earth, Lam. 4.2.</hi> and the <hi>heirs of Glory</hi> been <hi>accounted but as Sheep for the Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> Pſal. <hi>44.22. Peter Martyr,</hi> in <hi>Rom. 8.36.</hi> thus gloſſes the Words; <hi>That they are not preſerved as ſome Sheep, for their Wooll and Lambs; but are like other Sheep, fed and fatted, that their Bodies may be for Meat. Scultetus</hi> thus understands the Words, in <hi>Pſal. 44.22. That the Wicked of the World do make no more to kill the Saints of God, than a Butcher doth to kill Sheep.</hi> The Bodies of the Saints have been laid as the mire of the Streets, and their Blood poured out as Water on the Ground, and Wicked Men have been permitted to do to ſome of them even as they would. Read <hi>Iſa. 51. laſt. Pſal. 79.3. Matth. 17.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> This being the State of the Church of God (for the moſt part) in the World, how neceſſary is it that every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould be armed with Faith and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb facs="tcp:54706:4"/>that the Truths of God ſhould be deeply rooted in our Souls, that they may ſerve as an Helmet to guard our Heads in a great Fight of Afflictions, and as an Anchor to eſtabliſh our Hearts in a grievous Storm of Perſecutions? Theſe following Conſiderations may ſomewhat conduce to this great End.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Christians ſhould conſider, That Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ was not of this World, neither is his <hi>Kingdom of this World, John 18.36.</hi> and he repreſents and commends his Diſciples to his Father as conformed to him in this, <hi>John 17.14, 16. They are not of the World, even as I am not of the World.</hi> Chriſt did but <hi>Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle (John 1.14.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) in our frail Fleſh, and paſſed through the World as a Pilgrim and Stranger: And all the Goſpel-Worſhip of Chriſtians is ſet out by <hi>keeping the Feaſt of Tabernacles, Zech. 14.16.</hi> And what doth this Expreſſion import? Surely this, among other things, may be hinted to us by this Text, That as we are moſt gratefully to acknowledge this great Mercy of the Son of God's Tabernacling in our Fleſh; ſo, that it ought to have this Effect upon us, to make us to ſojourn in the
<pb facs="tcp:54706:4"/>World as Pilgrims and Strangers, in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of a glorious Life, and Inheritance in Heaven. We ſhould account, that this Natural Life is not our Life, but that <hi>our Life is hid with God in Chriſt, Col. 3.3.</hi> That this Earth is not our Country, and that Worldly Enjoyments are not our Portion and Treaſure. Chriſt hath cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied our Old Man, and aboliſhed the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Life by his Death, <hi>Rom. 6.6.</hi> Chriſt hath put an end to the old State<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Week, and World; and by Riſing again the Firſt Day of the Week, he hath begun a new Week and World. The Eternal Day doth dawn, Immortality is brought to light, Everlaſting Life is begun and exemplified in the Reſurrection of Jeſus Christ: And he is aſcended to Heaven, to chuſe the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of, and prepare a place for all the Family and Houſhold of Faith, <hi>Pſal. 47.3.</hi> To this Jeſus we are called to <hi>go forth;</hi> on this Magnetick and Glorious Object are we to fix our Eyes and Hearts. If the Wiſe Men acknowledged him as King when he lay in a contemptible Cradle, and the Thief addreſſed to him as ſuch when he hung on an ignominious Croſs, ſhall not we much more confeſs and adore him now,
<pb facs="tcp:54706:5"/>
               <hi>crowned with Honour and Glory, and ſitting on the Right hand of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty on High?</hi> Shall we dote on a World that is a ſink of Sin, and a Scene of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity? Shall be we fond of the vile and baſe Life of the Firſt, diſlike and diſparage the glorious Life of the Second <hi>Adam?</hi> Shall we be charmed by, or chained to poor beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly Objects below, and deſpiſe the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Portion and rich Inheritance of Christ above? Shall a ſhort Life, clogged with Sin, clouded with Sorrows, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>tered with continual Temptations and Warfare, be preferred before a Life of Immortality, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobled with glorious Holineſs, perfect Peace, and triumphant Joy.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Chriſtians ſhould conſider what this World is, and the Men of it are; That they are called out from the World, it ſelf is devoted to the Fire, <hi>this Earth muſt be burnt up, 2 Pet. 3.10.</hi> And ſhall we feed on that which muſt be reduced to Aſhes? Shall we lay up our Treaſure and Portion where the Flames will devour and conſume all? And what are the unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Men of this World, but Spiritual Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſes, dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes? <hi>Strabo,</hi> in his <hi>Geography, lib. 17.</hi> tells us of a
<pb facs="tcp:54706:5"/>City in <hi>Egypt,</hi> calle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Dead Men,</hi> becauſe of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Dead Bodies that were Embalmed there: And he ſpeaks of the City of <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, lib. 13.</hi> That the Inhabitants were ſo pale, that <hi>Stratonicus</hi> ſaid of them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>That Dead Men walked about.</hi> And is it not ſo here? Men that are dead in Sin, walk about, and perform onely the Acts of the Natural Life. The World is ſaid to <hi>lye in Wickedneſs, 1 John 5.19.</hi> as dead <hi>Lazarus</hi> is ſaid to <hi>lye in the Grave, John 11.41.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Verb is uſed in the first place, and the Participle of the ſame Verb in the other. This corrupt World is ſet out by the Dead Sea, <hi>Ezek. 47.10.</hi> in which no Fiſh did live: <hi>Engedi</hi> and <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaim,</hi> there mentioned, were Places that did lye, one at the beginning, the other at the end of the Dead Sea, where <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorra</hi> stood of old; and on the Banks of it Spiritual Fiſhermen are ſaid to ſtand to draw Men out of this Dead Sea, into Communion with Chriſt the Prince of Life. The Cities of the blind Gentiles are ſaid to be <hi>deſolate, Iſa. 54.3.</hi> becauſe there were none in them that did live the Life of God:
<pb facs="tcp:54706:6"/>And the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaks of Wicked Men as dead Carcaſes, when he ſaith, <hi>The Pit is digged for them, Pſal. 94.13.</hi> And ſhall we not come forth from ſuch a World to Jeſus Chriſt? As God ſaid of beſieged <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> of old, <hi>Jer. 38.2.</hi> That <hi>he that ſtaid in the City ſhould die by the Famine or Peſtilence; but he that did go forth and yield to the King of</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, <hi>ſhould live:</hi> So thoſe that stay in this City of the World, muſt be condemned and periſh, <hi>1 Cor. 11.32.</hi> but thoſe that go forth, and ſubmit to Jeſus Christ, ſhall be ſaved, and live for ever, <hi>Heb. 5.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> We ſhould conſider what Jeſus Christ endured for us, <hi>Heb. 12.3.</hi> How great a Perſon was he? What provoking Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions did he ſuffer, and that from baſe Worms, and for vile Sinners? <hi>He ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied himſelf for our ſakes,</hi> to be a Priest and Sacrifice, <hi>John 17.19.</hi> He was whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for us; he was born, died; roſe again, aſcended to Heaven, intercedes there, and will come again, for the good of his People, <hi>Iſa. 9.6. Rom. 4. laſt. Heb. 6. laſt. Heb. 7.25. John 14.2, 3.</hi> This precious Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation was laid low in the Earth, for us to build on; this Noble Grain of Corn was
<pb facs="tcp:54706:6"/>ſowed in the Dust, that we might ſpring up from him to Everlasting Life: This excellent Bunch of Grapes was cast into the Wine-preſs of the Wrath of God, that we might drink new Wine with him in the Kingdom of his Father: This generous Stock was wounded and cut, that we as Grafts might be joyned to him, and live in him for ever. Do we believe? Or can we think on theſe things, and yet stick at any Service, or recoil from any Sufferings for the ſake of Jeſus Christ?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Let us conſider how Honourable the Sufferings of Saints for Christ are, <hi>Gal. 6.17. I bear about in my body the marks of the Lord Jeſus;</hi> the print of the Stripes and Wounds he had ſuffered for Christ's ſake. Saints may much more glory in theſe, than Soldiers do in the Scars of their Wounds. Was it not more Honourable for ſome of the clean Creatures preſerved in the Ark, afterwards to be offered in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God by <hi>Noah,</hi> than for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Creatures to ſurvive them, or, for other Creatures to periſh in the Deluge? <hi>Gen. 8.20.</hi> Sufferings for Christ are part of our conformity to him in bearing the Croſs, and Testimonies of our Adoption,
<pb facs="tcp:54706:7"/>that being choſen out of the World, and called into the Kingdom of Christ, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Earthly Men hate and abhor us, <hi>John 15.19.</hi> The Sufferings of Saints are ſhort, their Evil things are meaſured by days, <hi>Pſal. 94.12, 13.</hi> but their Good and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs is commenſurate to Eternity, <hi>2 Cor. 4.17.</hi> They drink of a Cup of Afflictions, but it is a Cup like Christ's in this, that it paſſes away by our drinking of it, <hi>Matth. 26.4.</hi> Wicked Men ſhall drink of the Cup of Wrath, and yet it ſhall always abide at their Lips; but Saints ſhall drink of Christs Cup of Sufferings, and the Cup ſhall paſs away, their Tears ſhall be dried up, their Warfare ſhall be finiſhed; ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and ſighing ſhall fly away; <hi>Weeping ſhall endure but for a Night, Joy ſhall come in the Morning, Pſal. 30.5.</hi> After the ſmoaking Furnace of Bondage and Sufferings, ſhall come the burning Lamp of Deliverance and Liberty, <hi>Gen. 15.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> God ſees and will reward the Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his Saints, <hi>Rom. 8.18. 2 Cor. 4.17.</hi> Though God doth ſet forth ſome of his People as <hi>men appointed to death, 1 Cor. 4.9.</hi> yet he hath not appointed them to Wrath, but to obtain Salvation by Jeſus
<pb facs="tcp:54706:7"/>Chriſt, <hi>1 Theſſ. 5.9.</hi> The Plowers indeed make long Furrows on them, but God ſowes them with the Promiſe of Everlaſting Life; while Men think to deſtroy their Gold of Grace, God is refining them from their Droſs of Corruption; while Enemies would blow away the good Wheat that is in them, God is winnowing them from their Chaff. As <hi>Xerxes</hi> ſtood on the Shore, and beheld the Sea-fight of his Men with the <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and when any of his Captains fought valiantly, he had his Scribes by him, to write down his Name, and the Name of his City and Ship, that he might reward him: (<hi>See</hi> Herod. <hi>Hiſt. 1.8.</hi>) So Chriſt is on the calm Shore of a bleſſed Eternity, he beholds all the Courage and Conflicts of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, he regiſters all in his Book, and takes it on account, in order to an eternal Reward.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> Conſider the Benefit that hath accru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Church, and the Advantage that hath redounded to the Kingdom of Chriſt, by ſuffering Saints. When Saints have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered Death for Chriſt, their Carcaſes have enriched and fatted the Ridges of <hi>Zion's</hi> Field, their Blood hath watered the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of <hi>Immanuel</hi>'s Land, and made it more fruitful: When theſe Grains of Corn
<pb facs="tcp:54706:8"/>have fallen to the Earth, and died, many more have ſprung up in their room. <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> in <hi>Rom. 8.36.</hi> excellently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <hi>That the Goſpel hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated in the World by Miracles and Torments; by Works done above the Power of Nature, and by cruel Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, patiently and joyfully endured, beyond the ſtrain or ſtrength of Fleſh and Blood.</hi> Theſe were wonderful Atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations to, and Confirmations of the Truth of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi> Let us conſider, That Chriſt's Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſhall at laſt be prevalent, victorious, and triumphant. Crafty Worldlings deſire to be of the ſtrongeſt ſide; The <hi>Decree of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> Pſal. <hi>2.7.</hi> and the <hi>Zeal of the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> is for the Eſtabliſhing of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> Iſa. <hi>9.7.</hi> The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions indeed have their time, and are angry with Chriſt and his People; but the time of his Wrath will alſo come, <hi>Rev. 11.18.</hi> when he will tread them under his Feet, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and deſtroy them for ever, <hi>Pſal. 110.1. Pſal. 21.8, 9. Luke 19.27.</hi> God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath promiſed to make all Chriſt's Foes to be his Foot-ſtooll: <hi>Though</hi> Jacob <hi>be but a Worm, yet ſhall he threſh the
<pb facs="tcp:54706:8"/>Mountains, Iſa. 41.14, 15.</hi> And though <hi>Zion</hi> be as a Tabernacle, weak and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible in the Eye of the World, yet its Stakes ſhall not be removed, nor its Cords broken. Chriſt muſt reign, till he hath ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued all his Enemies: And though to ſerve Chriſt's Kingdom, ſeems to be as the Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's Veſſel, and his Enemies ſeem to have the Rod of Iron to daſh it to pieces; yet Faith hath another View and Proſpect of Things, it beholds all the adverſe Powers of the World but as a frail Potter's Veſſel, and Chriſt as having the Rod of Iron, and an Almighty Arm to uſe it, for the daſhing of them to pieces.</p>
            <p>This Treatiſe, <hi>My Lord,</hi> that I humbly preſent to Your Honour, is not unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. If we look abroad into the World, we may perceive, that God hath made many <hi>Shilohs</hi> among the <hi>Proteſtant Churches, Jer. 7.12.</hi> and he ſends us to thoſe <hi>Shilohs,</hi> to behold their Ruines and Deſolations. We yet ſtand on the Shore, and behold the Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracks of others; but if he that Parks in the wild Ocean, and treads its mountainous Waves into a ſmooth Plain, doth not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, we may quickly feel and taſte the ſame Fruits of Antichriſtian Rage &amp; Fury.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:54706:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> I have Dedicated this ſmall Piece to Your Honour, as a Token of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, and as a Teſtimony of my Gratitude to You, for Your Favour and Kindneſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed towards me, who am one of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of the Servants of Chriſt. As the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of the Law did not diſcharge the Debt of Sinners, but were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Col. 2.14.</hi> a Hand-writing, or Bond, by which they confeſſed themſelves obnoxious to God their Great Creditor; ſo I preſume not to pay my Debt by offering Your Honour this ſmall Treatiſe, but to recogniſe my Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations, and to confeſs my Engagements to Your Lordſhip. That the Wing of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence may overſhadow Your outward, and that the Well of Life may refreſh Your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man; That You may be eſtabliſhed in the ſound Belief and exemplary Practice of Goſpel-Truths, and ſo feel the Power and taſte the ſweetneſs of them, for Your Eternal Comfort and Happineſs, it is the earneſt Deſire, and it ſhall be the ſervent Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Febr. <hi>7. 1681.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>My Lord, Your moſt Humble and Obliged Servant,</hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL TOMLYNS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54706:9"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. 13.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let us go forth therefore unto him without the Camp, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Reproach.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the Twelfth Verſe the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Author of this Epiſtle ſpeaks of the Sufferings of Chriſt, as prefigured and typified by the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Sacrifice for ſin, that was Offered by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> High-Prieſt on the day of Attonement: That Sacrifice was not offered on the Altar, as other Sacrifices were, but was burnt without the Camp, only the blood of the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was brought into the moſt Holy Place, to make Reconciliation for ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; and for this end was ſprinkled on,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 16.14.</note> and before the Mercy Seat; and the Fat of the Sin-Offerings only was burnt on
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54706:10"/>the Altar, <hi>Lev.</hi> 16.25. but the Fleſh and Skins both of the Bullock and of the Goat that were offered for ſin, were to be carried without the Camp, and there to be burnt, <hi>Lev.</hi> 16.27. <hi>vid. Lev.</hi> 4.12, 21.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſolemn Anniverſary Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, offered on the great day of Attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (being the tenth day of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Month) did not only ſhadow out the Nature of Chriſt's Sacrifice, <hi>viz.</hi> that he was to be a Sacrifice for ſin, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>laſt,</hi> but did alſo point at the very place of his Sufferings; that he ſhould be carried without the Gates of the earthly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and there be put to death. When the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> were Travellers in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Sacrifice was burnt without the Camp; but when they arrived at, and were ſetled in <hi>Canaan,</hi> then the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice was burnt without the Gates of the City of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> And Jeſus Chriſt, to fulfill this Type, ſuffered without the Gate.</p>
            <p>The Divine Penman of this Epiſtle proceeds, in the words of the Text, to improve the Doctrine that he had
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54706:10"/>delivered concerning Chriſt's ſuffering without the Gate, and on it doth ground an excellent Exhortation, and preſs a weighty Duty, to wit, To <hi>go forth to Jeſus without the Camp, bearing of his reproach.</hi> The Sufferings of Chriſt were not only expiatory, but alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary; they did not only ſerve to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe God, but alſo to inſtruct and animate men to tread in his ſteps, to imitate his pattern, to bean his Croſs: As Chriſt was an Abject, ſo his people muſt expect to be Out-caſts; the world that was ſo unkind to him, will not be friendly towards them; as he was treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as unworthy to live among men, ſo they muſt reckon to be caſt out as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet to be accounted and reputed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as Parts of the Common-wealth, or Members of the Church; they muſt look to drink of Chriſt's Cup, and to be baptized with his Baptiſm;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.36. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.9.</note> and ſo account themſelves as Sheep for ſlaughter, as men devoted to death, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Malefactors going without the Gate to Execution.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:54706:11"/>
            <p>In the words we may obſerve theſe ſeveral Parts:</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Duty urged and enforced on the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> in which the Author of this Epiſtle doth comprize and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend himſelf; <hi>Let us go forth to Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The place to which they were to go; <hi>viz. without the Camp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. We have the difficulty of this Duty, and what it will coſt us to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with it, we muſt ſhare in the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and ignominy of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> To be ſeparated from the world, to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed againſt, to be hooted and point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at by men, to be ſpoiled, impriſoned, condemned, and executed as vile Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, as infamous Malefactors, carries in it a great deal of ſhame in the Eye of ſenſe: When the people of God do ſuffer hard things, they that are either actors in their Tragedies, or ſpectators of their Miſeries, are very prone and ready to conclude that they have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſome great evil of ſin, and ſo deſerved this evil of puniſhment. <hi>I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.9.) <hi>as an evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doer, even unto Bonds.</hi> And Chriſt fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54706:11"/>to his Diſciples, that the men of the world ſhould <hi>caſt out their names as evil, Luke</hi> 6.22. and elſewhere, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.10, 11. he intimates, that Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſhould <hi>revile them, and ſpeak all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of evil falſly againſt them, for his names ſake.</hi> Nothing is more ordinary and common, than that the world ſhould calumniate, brand, and black thoſe that will not wear its Livery, and ſhape themſelves after its Manners and Example.</p>
            <p>And in theſe words <hi>[bearing of his reproach]</hi> we may diſcern and eſpy a motive and argument, ſecretly couched, to encourage and animate them to <hi>go forth to Jeſus, and to bear reproach;</hi> for it is <hi>his reproach,</hi> we are no worſe uſed and treated than our Lord was; we are but conformed to him in ignominy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilings: Was the Prince of life, the King of glory, thus clouded and eclipſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thus blackt and ſtigmatized by the world? and ſhall we be tender of our Names? ſhall we doat on our Credit, or be fond of our Reputation? ſhall we ſhrink and recoil from ſufferings and reproaches, when the Son of God ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54706:12"/>and yielded to them; when the great Captain of our Salvation paſſed through them to his Glory? O ſhall not this exceedingly hearten us to bear the Croſs, to endure reproaches, when we imitate and follow Chriſt in all this, when he will account our ſufferings and reproaches to be his, and will charge and puniſh wicked men, as having ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, reviled, and perſecuted him in all they have done to us?</p>
            <p>The Doctrine that I ſhall inſiſt on from the words, is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is the Duty of Chriſtians to go forth to Jeſus without the Camp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three things are here to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is meant by <hi>the Camp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What it is to <hi>go forth without the Camp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. How Chriſtians are ſaid to <hi>go forth to Jeſus without the Camp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. What is here meant by <hi>the Camp?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By <hi>the Camp</hi> I underſtand Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Towns, and the Society of the men of the world that live in them. There is in the word <hi>Camp</hi> an alluſion to the Camp of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54706:12"/>And the phraſe intimates the temporary, ſhort, and mutable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men in this world: Though men have ſtrong Houſes, ſtately and beautiful Cities, yet all theſe are to be reputed but as weak Tents, as a Camp pitched down for a Night or two, and then ſuddenly removed. It's true, the men of this world would ſtay here, and ſix their abode below on this earth; and when the Scripture paints out their inward deſires and carnal affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it deſcribes them as <hi>dwellers on earth, Luke</hi> 21.35. when as Saints are ſet forth but as <hi>ſojourners,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. and confeſs themſelves <hi>Pilgrims and Strangers, Heb.</hi> 11.13. yet when the truth of their ſtate is repreſented to us, then they are ſet forth but as Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers through the world, and their Houſes are but as Tents, their Towns and Cities are but as a Camp, that they lodge in, in their paſſage towards Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <hi>The world paſſeth away and the luſts thereof,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.17. <hi>The faſhion of the world paſſeth away,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31. Look to the Heavens above, to the Earth beneath, the Heavens ſhall vaniſh
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54706:13"/>away like ſmoke, the Earth ſhall wax old as a Garment, the inhabitants of it ſhall dye in like manner: There is nothing viſible but what is mutable, flitting and fading; we have no ſolid baſis, no ſure foundation to reſt on, till we come to Gods ſalvation that ſhall be for ever, and to his righteouſneſs that ſhall not be aboliſhed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.6. As Saints are ſaid to have their Camp, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9. ſo we read of the Tents of Wickedneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.10. None have any ſure continuing and abiding ſtate in this world, all are travelling from hence, and journying towards another world: but yet this is intimated in the phraſe, that wicked men ſeem in the eye of ſenſe to be in a far better ſtate here, than the people of God; they are as Souldiers at reſt in their Camp, well lodged and accommodated in their Tents, under covert and ſhelter, in ſafeguard and ſecurity, not obnoxious to dangers and Enemies, as Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſeem to be, that are turned and ſhut out of this Camp, that are expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the rage of a fierce and purſuing Enemy, that are driven to and fro,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54706:13"/>hurried up and down in the world, and may eaſily be gleaned, ſoon pickt up and deſtroyed, as Souldiers that ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle from an Army, or are ſhut out of the Camp. The Apoſtle excellently deſcribes his own and others ſtate that were gone out of the Worlds Camp, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Even unto this preſent hour we both hunger and thirſt, and are naked, and are buffetted, and have no certain dwelling place.</hi> Wicked men are often as Souldiers well defended by the walls of their Camp, when Gods Saints are expoſed to ſtorms of ſufferings, to the inroads and invaſions of Enemies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What is it to <hi>go without this Camp?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, Several things are meant by this expreſſion:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Hebrews</hi> are exhorted to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Temple, the Ceremonial Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the Moſaical Pedagogy: Not to cleave to, or build upon thoſe Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices or Ceremonial Worſhip that was carried on within the walls of the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and that the Prieſts were daily converſant about in the Temple; but by Faith to go forth to the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt, by Faith to cleave to,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54706:14"/>feed upon that as all-ſufficient for the purging of their guilt, the filling and ſatisfying of their ſouls. The very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering and burning ſome Sacrifices for ſin, on the ſolemn day of Attonement (no part of which did redound to the Levitical Prieſts, and that they had no right to eat of) did point at the great and true Sacrifice of the Meſſiah; the benefit of which ſhould not accrue or be imparted to thoſe that did ſtill ſtick to the Sacrifices of the Law, and adhere to the Moſaical Ceremonies, and ſeek their reconciliation and ſalvation by repeating of them, and continuing in the practice of them. If men ſtick to, and truſt on any thing but Chriſt and his Sacrifice, for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and juſtification before God, they hereby cut themſelves off from Chriſt, and have no right to the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his Sacrifice: He will not ſhare the glory of our Juſtification with brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Sacrifices, or mens own Works. <hi>O fooliſh Galatians</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 3.1.) <hi>who hath bewitched you, that you ſhould not obey the Truth!</hi> that is, that you ſhould not, according to the Goſpel, truſt on,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54706:14"/>and cleave to Chriſt and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs only for your juſtification and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance before God? Hath not Chriſt been evidently ſet forth as crucified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eyes? Hath not the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Sorrows and Sufferings of the Son of God, have not the ends and deſign of his Death been in a lively manner painted out before your Eyes? And can you think after all this, that Chriſt will admit Moſaical Ceremonies, or Man's Works, to be Partners with him in the Great Work of Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Is there any need of Mixtures or Additions of our own to be joined to the Sacrifice of Chriſt, as a ſupplement to ſupply any defect that is in the Death of Chriſt, as to the attaining of this great end of our Juſtification? No, we muſt renounce all Ceremonies, Sacrifices, Works of our own, and go out to Jeſus, and adhere only to his Sacrifice, for the purifying of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and removing of our Guilt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When the Apoſtle ſaith we ſhould go out from the Camp, he means we ſhould Renounce and be ready to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh the Favour, the Friendſhip,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54706:15"/>the Society of the Men of this World; and when we cannot poſſeſs and enjoy them, and yet be Faithful to Jeſus Chriſt, to go forth from Towns and Cities, and bereave our ſelves of our Houſes, Eſtates, and outward World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Comforts, when we cannot retain them without diſhonouring Chriſt, wounding Conſcience, ſtaining our Garments, and hurting our Souls. Our Love to Chriſt muſt be the Reigning, Sovereign, and Supreme Love in our Souls, and muſt give Rules and Laws how long we ſhall retain, and when we ſhall diſmiſs and caſt away outward things. When they tempt us from Chriſt, to ſtay with, and cleave to them, we muſt grow jealous of them; and our jealouſie muſt be cruel as the Grave, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6. Then we muſt hate and forſake whatever is ſweet and dear to the Natural Man, and is like to prove a fatal ſnare to our ſouls, a bribe from Satan to buy off our love from Chriſt, and to tempt us from our Loyalty to this glorious King, and from our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity to our heavenly Husband; in this caſe we muſt turn the world out of our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54706:15"/>hearts, caſt it out of our hands, throw all things below behind our backs, and follow Chriſt. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> may be ſaid <hi>go without the Camp,</hi> when he renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and relinquiſhed the Honours of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Court, all the Pleaſures and Treaſures of <hi>Egypt,</hi> joining himſelf to his Brethren that were the Servants, Worſhippers, and People of God. He might have kept himſelf in <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Court and Palace, and been uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned at the burdens and bondage of the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> he might have lived as in a ſtrong and ſafe Camp: But <hi>he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be called the Son of</hi> Pharaoh<hi>'s Daughter, and choſe rather to ſuffer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions with the People of God, than to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin that were but for a ſeaſon; eſteeming the Reproach of Chriſt greater Riches than the Treaſures of Egypt, Heb.</hi> 11.24, 25, 26. So thoſe eminent Saints and Worthies that we read of <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37, 38. did <hi>go forth without the Camp,</hi> when they left Cities and Towns, forſook their Houſes, and wandred up and down in Deſarts and Wilderneſſes, were clothed but with Sheep-skins and Goats, and had no other Chambers or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54706:16"/>Beds to lodge in but Caves and Dens of the earth; they had hard Fare, vile Rayment, and bad Lodging, while o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had delicious Feaſts, coſtly and gorgeous Garments, warm Chambers, and ſoft Beds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But how may it bee ſaid that Chriſtians <hi>go forth without the Camp,</hi> or that it is their own voluntary and free act, when indeed the world caſts and drives them out? as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.5. <hi>Your Brethren hated you, and caſt you out for my Names ſake. John</hi> 9.34. it is ſaid, the Phariſees and Jews caſt out the man that ſpake honourably of, and gave glory to Chriſt. So <hi>Luke</hi> 6.22. <hi>They ſhall ſeparate you from their Company, and caſt out your Names as evil:</hi> In theſe words Chriſt ſeems to allude to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Jews, that when they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated a man, did blot out his Name from their Publick Regiſters and Records, as a man that was ſpiritually dead, and no longer to be reputed as a Member of their Church or Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue. So that it ſeems the world ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trudes and impoſes ſufferings on the People of God; how then are they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54706:16"/>exhorted, or ſaid <hi>to go out of the Camp?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe things may well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt together, and do not juſtle or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict each other; as 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. the Prieſts are ſaid to thruſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> out of the Temple, and yet he himſelf is ſaid to haſte to be gone, as he was willing to withdraw in the ſenſe of Gods hand ſtretched out againſt him; ſo the World caſts out, and yet Saints <hi>go out without the Camp.</hi> The Men of this Earth are bent and rage againſt the Saints of the Moſt High; yet if they would recede from the Truth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline from the pure Worſhip of Jeſus Chriſt; if they would ſend an Ambaſſy to the World, pray for conditions of Peace, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.32. be brought to their Lure, and ſtoop to their Wills, they might be reconciled to their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and gain their Favour, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35. They were tortured, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not of deliverance: after they had ſome taſte of Torments, ſome ſence and feeling of Anguiſh and Pain, their Enemies ceaſed a little time from their cruelty, gave them ſome reſpite and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54706:17"/>interval of Eaſe, and then fell to col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loguing with them, and alluring of them, and making them fair. Promiſes of Life and Preferment, if they would deſert Gods Truth and Worſhip, and comply with their Will; but theſe Spiritual Champions diſdain ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers and Terms; <hi>They accepted not of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, that they might obtain a better Reſurrection.</hi> So Chriſts ſincere Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples do in Chriſts Language take up their Croſs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.24. as they chuſe rather to ſuffer than to ſin; <hi>to go without the Camp</hi> and pleaſe God, than to ſtay in it and diſpleaſe him: there needs no other Cords but their own fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Love to Chriſt, and their fixed purpoſes to be faithful to him, to bind theſe voluntary Sacrifices to the Altar of ſufferings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.27.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How, and in what ſenſe, may Chriſtians be ſaid <hi>to go forth to Jeſus without the Camp?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> When we own Chriſts Truth, avow his Ways, adhere to his ſure and ſpiritual Worſhip, join our ſelves to him by a firm and lively Faith, and cleave to him with full purpoſe of Heart, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54706:17"/>all things for him, then we go to Jeſus; hereby we declare whoſe we are, to whom we belong, and whom we will follow even to the Death: We go forth to Jeſus, when we are ready to be bound, and to die for his ſake; when we are conformed to him in Sufferings, and ſubmit to be uſed and treated by the World as Jeſus Chriſt was: He was no Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen, Darling, or Favourite of this World, as ſoon as Born he experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented what the courteſie, he taſted what the kindneſs of the World was to him; there was no room for him in the Inn; he was thruſt out into the Stable; and laid in a Manger: Afterwards the Worlds enmity did more ripen, and riſe to a greater height, he was filled with Sorrows, loaded with Sufferings, crowned with Throns, bathed in his own Blood: Theſe were the Fruits that Heavenly Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-man received from his own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Vineyard: and when we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to have Fellowſhip with Chriſt in his Tribulations, then we go forth to him, when we are contented to bear
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54706:18"/>reproaches and diſgraceful Sufferings from the World, for his ſake to be cut off from the Eſteem, Favour, and Society of the World; to be exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from their Company, Dainties, and Delights; to be removed from Men as Lepers, and condemn'd Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors, (for ſuch were diſgraceful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly turned out of the Camp of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.10.14. <hi>Lev.</hi> 24. <hi>v.</hi> 23.) as Chriſt was carried without the Gate, being condemned to Death, as if he had been a Blaſphemer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and a Traytor againſt <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But here it may be queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, how Chriſtians can be ſaid to go forth to Jeſus without the Camp? Doth he ſtill ſtand without the Camp, is he yet Suffering without the Gate; or hanging on the Infamous Croſs, on the Fatal Tree?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, that the Perſonal Sufferings of Chriſt are at an end: God hath taken him from Priſon and Judgment: He hath raiſed him from the Grave, and exalted him at his Right Hand, Tears are wiped from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54706:18"/>his Eyes, and a Maſſy Glittering Crown is ſet on his Head. He is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into his Royal City and Palace, placed in his Throne, and Feaſted with all the delights of the Heavenly Paradiſe; but yet Chriſt ſuffers and is Perſecuted in his Members, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.4. <hi>Saul, Saul, why Perſecuteſt thou me?</hi> His Goſpel, his Intereſt, his People are diſcountenanced and frowned upon by the World; they are not entertained, but are rejected of the Men of this Earth, and in this reſpect Chriſt may ſtill be ſaid to ſtand without the Gate, and to be put without the Camp; his Truth, his Worſhip, his People are diſgraced, and diſdained by the World, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.14. His Citizens ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, after he was gone into a far Country, even into Heaven; and ſent a Meſſage after him, to expreſs they held the ſame fixed reſolution; that he ſhould not Reign over them: Mark this Expreſſion, <hi>they ſent a Meſſage af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him;</hi> they did not only declare their contempt and enmity to his Face when he was yet preſent as to his Humane Nature in the World; but
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54706:19"/>they continue their diſloyalty, they perſiſt in their Rebellion againſt him: They do not repent of their former rejection of him, and Cruelty practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on him; they are no better Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured towards him now he is in his Exaltation, then they were in his ſtate of Humiliation; they are as ſierce againſt, and injurious to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as they were to him in his own Perſon; ſo many Saints as they ſlay, ſo many Martyrs as they cut off, ſo many Meſſengers they ſend to Heaven, to relate to Jeſus Chriſt their obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Malice and Rebellion againſt him. As <hi>Stephen</hi> ſoon after Chriſt, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands of Saints that have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſince, have been ſent on this Meſſage to Heaven; to declare that the World will not have Jeſus Chriſt to Reign over them: And in this reſpect we may be ſaid ſtill in our Sufferings to go forth to Jeſus with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Gate. This I take to be the Senſe, principal ſcope and intendment of this Divine Writer in this Verſe, and therefore I ſhall ſuit my ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Diſcourſe to this, as the main
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54706:19"/>deſign of the words, and ſhall proceed to give Reaſons why Chriſtians muſt go forth to Jeſus, enduring contempt and Reproachful Sufferings for his ſake.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Chriſtians muſt go forth without the Camp to Jeſus; becauſe they are not of this World: Chriſt twice in that Excellent Prayer in the 17th of <hi>John</hi> mentions and inſiſts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this, <hi>John</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 14.16. <hi>they are not of the World, as I am not of the World;</hi> and the ſame words are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in the 16th Verſe; his People much needing the Care, Protection, and Comforts of the Father on this account: Believers are ſaid to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the Earth, from among Men, and out of every Kindred, Tongue, People, and Nation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.3, 4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Chriſt gave himſelf for their ſins, to deliver them from this preſent Evil World,</hi> Gal. 1.4. <hi>And he hath choſen them out of the World,</hi> John 15.19. that they may not continue, be condemned, and periſh for ever with the World; and ſhall not Saints by an Overt-act own and avow this
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54706:20"/>Truth, that they are not of the World; and be ready and willing to go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Camp; and by this declare they are not of the ſame Piece, are not of the ſame Spirit with the World; that though they have lived and converſed among the Men of the World, yet they are not of their Body and Fraternity, but being Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from their vain Converſation, and tranſlated into the Kingdom of Gods Dear Son, they are Related to him as Members to a Head, as Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to a King? When Saints leave their Habitations, Eſtates, and all converſe with the Men of the World for Chriſts ſake, they manifeſt they are not of the World, and that their Hearts, Hopes and Treaſure is not here below.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> All the Happineſs of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians is laid up in Chriſt: <hi>He is their life, Col.</hi> 3.4. <hi>The Lord their Righteouſneſs,</hi> Jer. 23.6. <hi>He is their Peace,</hi> Eph. 2.14. <hi>He is their hope,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.1. He dwells in them as the <hi>hope of Glory,</hi> Col. 1.27. Yea he is ſaid to be <hi>all, Col</hi> 3.11. Chriſt is all, and Chriſtians
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54706:20"/>are ſaid to be <hi>compleat in him,</hi> Col. 2.10. they have all that is neceſſary, excellent and truly deſirable in him, and therefore well may they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to <hi>forget their People, and their Fathers Houſe,</hi> to leave and forſake all for him, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 45.10. O! ſhall we not go forth to him that is our Life, Righteouſneſs, Peace, and hope of Glory?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> Chriſt for our ſakes was led without the Gate of the Earthly <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> Jeſus that he might Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie the People, Suffered without the Gate: If he had not carried our ſins, and expoſed himſelf to endure our Curſe, he could not have faln into the Hands of his Enemies, and been Nailed to the Croſs; it was our Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and his own love that made him ſo weak; otherwiſe all the Power of the World could not have impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sufferings on the Son of God, or have bound this Lamb of God to the Horns of the Altar. But he put in his own Name into our Bond; he became our Surety, and thereby caſt a Vail on his own Holineſs and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54706:21"/>and was not dealt withal by God as he was in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Holy,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>laſt. Iſ.</hi> 53.6.</note> harmleſs, unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, but as made ſin for us; our guilt being transferr'd, our Iniquities being laid on him: Thus he that knew no ſin in himſelf, became <hi>a Man of Sorrows and acquainted with Grief,</hi> Iſ. 53.3. he was as a Worm for the World to tread on, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 22.6. a mark for Men to ſhoot at;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.11, 12.</note> the true Ark of Salvation, not only aſſaulted with Waves below, but beat on with Storms from above; the Windows of Heaven were opened as well as the Fountains of the great Deep below were broken up: <hi>For it pleaſed the Lord to bruiſe him, he did put him to grief,</hi> Iſ. 53.10. he had not only a Baptiſm in a Sea of Sufferings without, but he drank in a Cup of unexpreſſible Sorrows. <hi>The Waters came into his Soul,</hi> Pſ. 69.1, 2. He complained in his Agony in the Garden, <hi>that his Soul was ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to the Death,</hi> Mat. 26.38. <hi>his Soul was troubled,</hi> John 12.27. And his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54706:21"/>was thus Vailed by our ſins, that our ſins might be Vailed by his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and covered by his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; he was the ſlain Goat, as he was delivered for our ſins; and he was the ſcape Goat, as he carried them quite away, <hi>and was raiſed again for our Juſtification,</hi> Rom. 4. <hi>laſt.</hi> The Sacrifices that were ſlain and burnt on the Day of Atonement, Figured Chriſts, as I have already intimated: Theſe Sacrifices were ſo charged and loaded with the ſins of the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in a Type, that he that carried them forth and burnt them without the Camp, was to waſh his Cloaths, and bathe his Fleſh in Water, and then be admitted into the Camp; ſo he that led forth the ſcape Goat on whom the Iniquities of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were laid, was to waſh his Cloaths and bathe his Fleſh in Water before he could be received into the Camp; they ſeemed ſo to be defiled by touching Sacrifices on whom the ſins of Men were laid; and ſo Chriſt was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and caſt out of the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as if he were a very
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54706:22"/>unclean, loathſome, and abominable Perſon; having yet no ſin of his own, but being burthened with the ſins of his People. O! what reproach was this, for Jeſus to be ſeparated and thruſt out from among the Citizens of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and then as a Sacrifice to be burned in the Fire of the Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance and Wrath of God without the Camp; as thoſe Sacrifices for ſin were burnt in Material Fire without the Gate, on the Day of Atonement! And this is further to be obſerved, that the Blood of theſe Beaſts, ſo charged with ſin, was yet brought into the moſt Holy Place in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to ſprinkle the Mercy Seat, and to make Atonement by it in a Type; even ſo though Chriſt died as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Perſon in the Eye of the World, and as one charged with the ſins of his People, in the account of God, yet his Blood as moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, is brought into the true Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Sanctuary, cries in the Ears of God, and is pleaded before his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Throne, for the blotting out our ſins, and the making our Peace with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54706:22"/>God. Thus our Tranſgreſſions (which are our true and real ſhame) and Reproaches are covered, and wiped away before the Lord: O! did Jeſus Chriſt die to take away thoſe ſins that would have been our Eternal Infamy and Reproach, and ſhall not we willingly go forth to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus without the Camp, bearing the juſt and undeſerved Reproaches from the World?</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> The World ſtill baniſhes Chriſt, thruſts and keeps him out from among them: This is their Language againſt God and his Son Chriſt, <hi>Come let us break their Bonds in ſunder, and caſt their Cords from us,</hi> Pſalm 2.1, 2, 3. <hi>Cauſe the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael <hi>to ceaſe from before us,</hi> Iſ. 30.11. <hi>We will not have this Man to Reign over us,</hi> Luke 19.14. his word hath no place in them, <hi>John</hi> 5.38.42. and the love of God and Chriſt dwells not in their Souls; and may I not here apply the words of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah, They have,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>rejected the Law of the Lord, and what Wiſdom is in them?</hi> Jer. 8.9. ſo I may ſay, the World rejects the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54706:23"/>Lord of this Law, and what Wiſdom or Excellency is there in them? O! ſhall we value the Favour, Eſteem the Friendſhip or Communion of ſuch a World as rejects Jeſus Chriſt?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi> Martyr.</note> It is related of Biſhop <hi>Ridley,</hi> that it repented him that he had Eaten and Drank, that he had accepted any Meat or Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment in the Houſe of a Princeſs that refuſed to hear the Goſpel Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when it was by him offered to her; and ſhall we Magnifie the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a World that is unkind to Jeſus Chriſt, will not yield to his Authority, entertain his Kingdom, ſubmit to his Laws, or accept of his Salvation? O! ſhould we not call that Place, and thoſe Perſons <hi>Ichabod,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. <hi>two laſt Verſes,</hi> that thruſt away Chriſt, will not ſuffer him to dwell and reign among them? Where is Glory, if Chriſt be excluded and kept out? what is Trade, Honour, Riches, if Chriſt be abſent? O! how deſolate, how ſolitary, how uncomfortable ſhould that place and people be to us, here we may not proteſs Chriſt, may not Worſhip
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54706:23"/>him, and enjoy Communion with him in his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces?
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.14.16. <hi>as the</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites <hi>and</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites <hi>came away to</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</note> If the World rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, would ſeparate us from Chriſt, and obſtruct our Converſe with him, how freely and readily ſhould we go out from ſuch a World. When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> by their Idolatry had highly provoked God, and done much to drive him away, and to berave themſelves of his Gracious Preſence among them, <hi>Moſes took the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle and Pitched it without the Camp, far off from the Camp, and thoſe that ſought the Lord went out of the Camp, unto the Tabernacle to Worſhip God,</hi> Exo. 33.7. So truly the World ſets up ſo many Idols of jealouſie in their Hearts, and ſo put the ſtumbling Block of their Iniquity before their Faces, that Chriſt cannot delight in them, or dwell among them; his Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle is (as I may ſo ſpeak) Pitched without this Camp, and ſhall we not go forth to the Tabernacle of Chriſt, and enjoy Communion with him; though by this we loſe a place in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54706:24"/>the Worlds Camp? O! will you not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt, and reſort to him? will you prize their Favour, or court their Friendſhip, that ſlight and reject Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt? As, <hi>Amos</hi> 7.10. the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Prieſt accuſeth <hi>Amos</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the Lord to the King of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>the Land was not able to bear his words.</hi> And Ezek. 3.7. <hi>the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>will not harken unto thee, for</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>they will not harken to me.</hi> Jer. 12.8. <hi>Mine Heritage is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me as a Lion in the Forreſt, it cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out againſt me, therefore he hated and forſook it.</hi> And ſhall we linger and ſtay in ſuch a Camp where God and Chriſt are not liſtened too, where the Word will not, cannot be born; where Sinners indeed cry out againſt God, when they pretend only to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt and revile Men? <hi>O Righteous Father</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>the World doth not know thee,</hi> John 17.25. As for Chriſt <hi>he was in the World, and the World was made by him, and yet it knew him not,</hi> John 1.10. <hi>and the Spirit of Truth the World cannot receive, becauſe it knoweth him not,</hi> John 14.17. And
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54706:24"/>ſhould we be much concerned or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, if ſuch a World doth not know us, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.1. but reproaches, and caſts us out?</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> We cannot be Faithful to Chriſt, or enjoy Communion with him for ever; if we do not go out to him without the Camp, if we do not venture and Sacrifice all for Chriſt; if we be aſhamed of him before Men, he will be aſhamed of us before his Father and his Holy Angels; if we deny him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.32, 33. he will deny us; but if we confeſs him he will confeſs us before his Father in the Great Day of Judgment: We cannot ſerve two Maſters, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.24. eſpecially when thoſe are contrary to each other, and each of them demands our whole Heart and Service; we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pleaſe God, Chriſt, and the World too. <hi>Know you not that the Friendſhip of this World is enmity with God? whoſoever therefore will be a Friend of the World, is the Enemy of God,</hi> Jam. 4.4. You cannot keep in with the World, but you muſt break with God; you cannot gratifie and oblige
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54706:25"/>the World to you, except you will faſhion your ſelves according to its Pattern and Example; you muſt drink in its Corruptions, ſtain your ſelves with its Filth, and run with them to the ſame exceſs of Riot, elſe they will exclaim againſt you, and ſpeak Evil of you, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.4. If you have not ductile Conſciences, flexible and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant Spirits and Tempers, if you cannot change, ſay and unſay, the World will not care for you; it will be hard (if not impoſſible) to keep in with the World: and that Soul is in a moſt dangerous caſe, that is fixed and reſolved in this, that he will be the Friend of the World, that he will not venture the Frowns of Men, or hazard his ſtake in the World, that will not ſuffer Shipwrack of his Intereſts and Concerns on Earth. If a Man be thus Principled and affected, he is the Enemy of God and Chriſt; he doth prefer ſomething elſe before and above them; he will ſwallow and practice that which is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grievous and diſpleaſing to God, rather than be undone by Men; and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54706:25"/>hereby he proclaims his Enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God; therefore this ſhould be rooted and riveted in our Hearts, that we muſt ſuffer with Chriſt, if we would Reign with him; we muſt be Faithful to the Death, if we would receive the Crown of Life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>This is a Faithful ſaying, that if we be Dead with Chriſt, we ſhall live with him; if we Suffer with him, we ſhall Reign with him; if we deny him, he will deny us.</hi> It is obſervable, how the Apoſtle uſhers in this Aſſertion, what a Character of Truth he puts on this Sentence: <hi>If we Suffer with him, we ſhall Reign with him; this,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is a Faithful ſaying:</hi> Why ſhould he preface thus theſe two Verſes, but becauſe he ſaw there was need of it? Fleſh and Blood can hardly ſwallow and digeſt this Doctrine of Suffering: How do men ſtretch their Wits to diſtinguiſh themſelves from under an Obligation to Sufferings? How do they dread and recoil from the Croſs? ſurely they may reign without ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; Chriſt will not be ſo hard to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54706:26"/>them, as to deny and reject them, if they ſhrink and comply in dangerous Times: But let not Men beguile and deceive themſelves; the Apoſtle is peremptory in this, he doth not, he cannot mince the Matter; this is a Faithful ſaying, if we ſuffer we ſhall reign with Chriſt; if you refuſe Chriſts Croſs, you refuſe his Crown.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> We ſhould go forth to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus without the Camp; for it is but little that we leave or loſe by own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and cleaving to Jeſus Chriſt: The Holy Ghoſt diſgraces, debaſes, and lays low all the Grandure and Glory of the World; by calling it a Camp: O! what a ſhort and muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing is a Camp! How eaſily is it removed, how ſoon is it gone? <hi>Our Life is but a Vapour that appeareth a little while, and then vaniſheth away,</hi> Jam. 4.14. <hi>Our Days on Earth are but as a Shadow that flieth away and there is no abiding,</hi> Job 14.2. 1 Chron. 29.15. <hi>Man is like the Flower and the Graſs of the Field; a Wind comes over it, and quickly withers this Flower, and blows out this Lamp of Life,</hi> Pſ. 103.15, 16.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54706:26"/>The Sentence is already paſt, <hi>Duſt thou art, and to Duſt thou muſt return,</hi> Gen. 3.19. <hi>The Body is dead by reaſon of ſin,</hi> Rom. 8.10. If God doth but looſe our Cords, our Tent will preſently drop down to the ground; if he ſay return, we muſt preſently lie down in the Duſt, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 90.3. If he give out the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.1. <hi>Let them go forth,</hi> there will be no continuing in the Camp, no ſtaying in the World; if you cleave and cling to the World never ſo faſt, if God ſaith, <hi>let them go forth,</hi> you muſt be removed from hence: Thoſe who embrace and hug their Earthly Comforts and Enjoyments moſt, muſt be ſtript and deprived of them whether they will or no: <hi>The wicked is driven away in his wickedneſs,</hi> Prov. 14.32. <hi>As the whirle wind paſſeth, ſo the wicked is no more,</hi> Prov. 10.25. <hi>He ſhall be driven from light into dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and chaſed out of the world,</hi> Job 18.18. <hi>His ſubſtance ſhall not continue, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall he prolong the perfection thereof upon the earth,</hi> Job 15.29. <hi>God ſhall likewiſe deſtroy thee for ever; he ſhall take thee away, and pluck thee out of thy
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54706:27"/>Dwelling-place, and root thee out of the Land of the living,</hi> Pſ. 52.5. In this Verſe we may obſerve an Elegant Climax: It is ſaid, God ſhall pluck a Wicked man out of his Dwelling-place; but yet may he not continue and flouriſh elſewhere? No, God ſhall root him out of the Land of the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: But if he be rooted out of the Land of the living, may he not find Favour and Mercy in another world? No, to this it is anſwered, <hi>God ſhall deſtroy thee for ever:</hi> God ſets the men of this Earth in ſlippery places, he caſts them down into deſtruction, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73.18. Thoſe that will not go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Camp to Jeſus, that hold faſt their Riches and Honours, how ſoon may they be bereaved of them? <hi>Micah</hi> 1.15. <hi>I will</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>bring an Heir unto thee, O Inhabitant of</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſhah: And what Heir is meant? By an Heir here the Lord intends Robbers, and Spoilers, which he would let looſe to break in upon them: ſuch Heirs as they never thought of or intended. When men, by their care and induſtry, have been like Birds laying up, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54706:27"/>filling their Neſts with Riches, as Eggs, a Robber may come and take all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, as <hi>Iſ.</hi> 10.14. the King of <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyria</hi> glorieth, <hi>My Hand hath found as a Neſt the Riches of the people; and as one gathereth Eggs that are left, have I gathered all the Earth:</hi> It will be our Wiſdom and Intereſt, to make a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Neceſſity: We muſt forſake theſe things whether we will or no; and is it not better to relinquiſh them for Chriſt, which will turn to our account, and unſpeakable advantage? And is it any great matter to leave a mutable Camp, a weak Tent? if we look upon things with a Spiritual Eye, and judge right judgment, we ſhall have very low thoughts of all Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Excellencies and worldly Glory: Obſerve how the Scripture repreſents theſe things, as paſſing and periſhing, <hi>Their Beauty ſhall conſume in the Grave from their Dwelling,</hi> Pſ. 49.14. <hi>Doth not their Excellency that is in them go away?</hi> Job 4.21. <hi>All Fleſh is Graſs; and all the goodlineſs thereof is as the Flower of the Field,</hi> Iſ. 40.6. <hi>When they die they ſhall carry nothing away, their Pomp
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54706:28"/>and their Glory ſhall not deſcend after them,</hi> Pſ. 49.17. And ſhould we ſtick at going out of ſuch a Camp, where Beauty conſumes, Excellency goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, all the Goodlineſs of the Fleſh fadeth, and all the Glory of it va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth away?</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> We ought to go forth to Jeſus; for then there will be a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py iſſue of all our Sufferings, a good return of our Venture, a full Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of all our Loſſes: Jeſus was led without the Gate, was put to a ſervile, ignominious, and painful Death; but did God leave him in the Hand, and under the Power of Enemies? Did he ſink under the burden of his Sorrows? Was he ſwallowed up in a Sea of Sufferings? Hath he not abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed Death? Hath he not overcome the World, led Captivity Captive, and Triumphed over the Malice of Earth, and the Rage of Hell? Is he not returned to his Father, arrayed with the Spoiles of his Enemies, and the Trophies of his Victory? Is he not entred gloriouſly into his Royal City above? <hi>Hath not Gods Salvation
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54706:28"/>ſet him up on high?</hi> Pſ. 69.29. And may we not with comfort look up to Jeſus Chriſt, Exalted at the Right Hand of God, as <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites,</hi> fighting in the Valley, might with hope look up to the lifted Hands, and elevated Rod of <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Mount? <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.8, 9, 10, 11, 12. As God did not deſert the Head Chriſt, ſo he will not forſake his Members: May we not ſee the Event of all our troubles in the iſſue of Chriſts Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings? May we not from his Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, gather matter of hope as to our ſucceſs? Thoſe that go forth to Jeſus, will he not lead them unto Glory? <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.10. Hath he not pray'd that they may be with him, <hi>John</hi> 17.24. and promiſed that he will come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and receive them to himſelf, that where he is, they may be alſo? <hi>John</hi> 14.23. Suffering Saints ſhall not always ſtand without the Gate; or be hurried up and down in this Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; Jeſus Chriſt will lead them to a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed City of Habitations, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 107.7. He will carry his Flock into delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Paſtures in the Paradiſe of God;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54706:29"/>he will lodge his Bretheren in his Fathers Houſe; he will conduct his Spouſe into that Royal Bride-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that is furniſhed, and gloriouſly adorned above: Saints ſhall come out of their great Tribulations, and be before the Throne for ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.14, 15. Crying, Pain and Sorrow, and all Afflictions will paſs away: <hi>Death ſhall be ſwallowed up into Victory: All Tears ſhall be wiped from their Eyes, and their reproach and rebuke ſhall be taken away, and ceaſe from all the Earth,</hi> Iſ. 25.8. The next words to the Text do mention an abiding City that Believers do look for, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.14. Jeſus was reproachfully led without the Gate of the earthly <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> that he might with Honour and Glory lead his Saints within the Gates of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> O! will you not prize this goodly and glorious City, <hi>whoſe Walls are Salvation, and whoſe Gates are Praiſe?</hi> Iſ. 60.19. Will you prefer a being in an uncertain and momentary Camp, before a place in an Eternal City? Do you dread the loſs of your Camp? And will you
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54706:29"/>not much more fear excluſion out of this Bleſſed City? <hi>John</hi> 12.42. <hi>They feared to confeſs Chriſt, leſt they ſhould be put out of the Synagogue:</hi> But ſhould we not much more dread to deny Chriſt, leſt we ſhould be ſhut out of the City of God? Would you have a place of Reſt, of Honour, of Eternal Pleaſures, after your Days of Vanity and Sorrow? O! then go out to Jeſus, and this Captain of Salvation will convey you ſafe to this deſirable and glorious City; where your Heads ſhall be Crowned with Honour, and your Hearts be filled with Triumphant joy for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. This may reprove thoſe that are unwilling to own and confeſs Chriſt, to go forth to him, or to appear for him: How many Formal Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans think they may tarry in the Camp, they may retain the friendſhip of the world, they may preſerve their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Profits, and Civil-Intereſts, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54706:30"/>yet keep in with Jeſus Chriſt too? As <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpeaks of ſome that judged they might, as in a Dance, go in the middle, leading Chriſt in one, and the World in the other hand. And God complains of the Idolatrous Jews, that <hi>they enlarged their Bed,</hi> Iſa. 57.8. as if they would make room for a lawful Husband and an Adulterer too: Are not too many thus affected, that as double-minded men waver, fluctuate, and ſtagger between God and the World, Chriſt and their own Carnal Intereſts? Theſe account it harſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, to be told they muſt go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Camp to Jeſus; that they muſt loſe their Friends, caſt off and deteſt their neareſt Relations, and turn their backs on all that is ſweet and dear to them in the World. O how do they find fault with, and cry out againſt theſe things as very unmeet and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to be impoſed on them: What, ſhall they be ruined and undone in the World for an Opinion or Practice of Religion? This is very hard and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to fleſh and blood; they would have Chriſt to come within the Camp
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54706:30"/>to them, they would not go without the Camp to him: They would have the Son of God to indulge them, and diſpenſe with them ſo far as may ſave their ſtake, and comply with their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal intereſt: They would reconcile God and the World; and ſo ſerve two Maſters, reap two Crops, and enjoy two Portions; have the beams of the Worlds favour, and the Light of Gods Countenance too: But how grievous and unpleaſant is it to hear that they muſt ſtrip themſelves of all ſeen things, for love to an inviſible Lord, and in expectation of a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Spiritual Happineſs? How doth the Fleſh murmur and repine at the leaving and loſs of all its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Poſſeſſions and Enjoyments? When men have laboured and toiled in the World to get an Eſtate, what ſhall they caſt all away in a moment, and not enjoy the Fruits of their labours? Yet thus Chriſts Diſciples did, they had toiled all Night, at laſt by Chriſts direction, caſting of their Nets, they had incloſed a great number of Fiſhes; yet they were not ſo pleaſed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54706:31"/>and delighted with this large and rich draught, but that when they came to the Shoar, <hi>they forſook all to follow Chriſt,</hi> Luke 5.6, 7.11. How con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary are thoſe then to this Doctrine and Duty, that would indent and compound with Chriſt, that he ſhould bring them a ſmoother and eaſier way to Heaven, than thoſe have gone, who through many Tribulations have entred into the Kingdom of God, and who will vary their Courſe as the Winds do ſhift and change, and follow Chriſt but as the Young-man did, who left his Garment and fled away naked, when Chriſts Enemies endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to take hold of him by it? <hi>Mark</hi> 13.51, 52. So when the world takes hold of them by the Garment of their Profeſſion, they leave it and fly away ſhamefully naked, as to their Souls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. This Doctrine ſhould put us on the Tryal and Examination of our ſelves; are we willing and ready to go forth to Jeſus without the Camp, bearing of his Reproach? In order to the diſcovering of the frame of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54706:31"/>your Hearts, and the truth of your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual State, let me propound a few ſerious Queſtions to you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. Have you ſet down and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the coſt, what it will ſtand you in to be Chriſtians indeed? Are you furniſhed with Spiritual Money in your Hearts, to go through with this Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to bring it to perfection? <hi>Luke</hi> 14.28, 29. Have you well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and weighed all the hazards, loſſes, and ſufferings that do attend the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity; that the Fine may riſe very high; the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace may be heated very hot? <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>For whom I have been Fine at all;</hi> or, as our Tranſlation, <hi>I have ſuffered the loſs of all things.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is taken by the <hi>Grecian</hi> Lawyers,
<note place="margin">vid. Zauch. in Locum.</note> for a Mulct and Fine. It is always a Crime in the Eye of the wicked World, to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from their corrupt ways, and cleave to Chriſts Truth and pure Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: When the world are reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; when the Hands of Wicked men are bound; then the Fine runs lower;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:54706:32"/>the men of this Earth only reproach and revile the People of God, for this reputed Crime of forſaking Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans Camp and Tents, and following Chriſt the Captain of Salvation. But there are Times when Satan is looſed; when the Dams are broken down, and the reſtraints are taken off from his Inſtruments; then a Flood of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Evils pours in upon the People of God: Now the Fine is increaſed, they are threatned with ſpoiling of Goods, loſs of Liberty and Life, if they will not deny Chriſt, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the inventions and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men: There are Seaſons when Sailing towards Heaven ſeems very dangerous in the Eye of Fleſh and Blood: As <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 27.9, 10. (When Sailing began to be danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, towards Winter) ſaith, <hi>Sirs, I perceive this Voyage will be with hurt and much dammage of the Lading of the Ship, and of our Lives.</hi> Even ſo men may perceive and diſcern ſuch Times, when the Voyage to Heaven is like to be with much Dammage of all the Wealth and Riches that they have
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54706:32"/>laded themſelves with; yea their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Lives may be loſt: Have you thought of ſuch cloudy times, of dark hours of temptation, of the gloomy Valley of the Shadow of Death, that God may try you whether you will caſt all over-board, to keep the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and peace of your Conſciences; ſuffer ſhipwrack of your Eſtates and Honours, rather than ſuffer ſhipwrack of Faith and your Integrity? You may lay the Foundation of your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual building in a peaceable time, in Halcyon days; but great ſtorms and fights of Affliction may ariſe and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize you before you have finiſhed your Building: As the Foundation of the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was laid in Peace, without oppoſition or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction from the World; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could finiſh it, their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies beſtirred themſelves, procured an Authority and Order from the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> againſt them, and ſpeedily put it in Execution, cauſing the <hi>Jews</hi> to ceaſe by force from proſecuting of this Building: Compute the 3. of <hi>Ezra</hi> the 8, 9, 10, 11. with 4. of <hi>Ezra</hi> 21.23. Thus
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:54706:33"/>it may be with you. Conſider there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whether your Hearts are fired, and your purpoſeſs fixed for Chriſt; Can you ſay with <hi>Paul, You are ready to be Bound and to die for the Name of the Lord Jeſus?</hi> Acts 21.13. Are you not rather reſolved againſt ſtanding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny brunt, bearing any hardſhip, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering any loſs for that Profeſſion? as <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th of <hi>France</hi> is ſaid to have ſpoken; that he would venture no further into the Sea of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but that he might ſtill ſee the Shoar, and retreat at his pleaſure to it. Have you not ſuch ſecret reſolutions as theſe; that you will not intereſt your ſelves too deeply, and ingage too far in any matter of Religion; but that you may make a fair and ſafe retreat if you ſee need? Or have you reckoned up all the troubles and loſſes that you may be expoſed to for Chriſt, and are come to this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 20.24. <hi>None of theſe things move me, neither do I account my life dear to me, that I may finiſh my Courſe with joy?</hi> Do you judge of all Loſſes and Afflictions, as <hi>Paul;</hi> that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54706:33"/>ſaid, <hi>I count the Sufferings of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time, not to be worthy to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the Glory that ſhall be revealed in us,</hi> Rom. 8.18. Are you reſolved to go forth to a Deſpiſed, Hated, and Perſecuted Jeſus; and with <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> to count your ſelves ſafer with Chriſt on the Waves, than in the Worlds Ship without him? <hi>Matt.</hi> 14.26, 28, 29.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 2. Have you ſold all for Chriſt? Matt. 13.44, 45. He that found the hidden Treaſures, for joy went and ſold all that he had, that he might buy the Field, and aſſure the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to himſelf: Chriſt is a Rich Treaſure, a Pearl of ineſtimable Price: O! have you found this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, this Pearl? Do you diſcern, eſpy, and know the Worth and Riches of Jeſus Chriſt? Are you ſo affected with him, as to ſell all for him? And what is it to ſell all for Chriſt? Surely it is to part with the eſteem, to relinquiſh the inordinate love of this world, or any thing in it. When the Market is faln, the Price of theſe things beaten down, as it were to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54706:34"/>buy thoſe Spiritual Goods that are imported by Chriſt the heavenly Merchant from another World: O! have your Souls ſuch a ſight of Chriſt and his Excellent Commodities, that you are weaned from your Eſtates and Lives, that you little value any thing here below; yea count all things but Dung that you may gain Chriſt? <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. If you have indeed thus ſold all things; it will not be very difficult to yield poſſeſſion; to quit the uſe and enjoyment of that which your Hearts are dead to: That which is truly put and turned out of your Hearts, will certainly be caſt out of your Hands in the day of Trial and Adverſity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 3. Are you indeed Married to Jeſus Chriſt? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. I have eſpouſed you to one Husband, even to Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4. that you may be Married to him that is raiſed from the dead: Hath he ſpoken and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your Hearts? Hath he allured and drawn your Souls to himſelf? In <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.2. God ſpeaks of the love of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Eſpouſals; That ſhe went up
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54706:34"/>after him, and followed him in a Wilderneſs, in a Land that was not ſown; where they might fear want, and feel Penury, without a miraculous and extraordinary Proviſion: If you are truly eſpouſed to Chriſt, you will follow him in a Wilderneſs. I have read an Hiſtory concerning the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gul,</hi> a Great Prince in the <hi>Eaſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> that grew jealous of his Son, leſt he ſhould aſpire to his Kingdom, and dethrone him in his abſence from his Imperial City: And therefore cauſed a Tower to be built, without any Gate or Door, yet well ſtored with all neceſſary Proviſions, in it to ſhut up his Son, during the time of his abſence: When this was underſtood, the Wife of this Young Prince de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to be ſhut up with her Husband in this Tower; ſuch was the great love that ſhe did bear to him. Thus if you love Chriſt as a Husband, you will go out to him; you will not be ſeparated and parted from him; but will ſay as <hi>Ittai</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.21. <hi>As the Lord liveth, where my Lord the King is, there will thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54706:35"/>be, whether in Life or in Death:</hi> As <hi>Rachel</hi> and <hi>Leah</hi> were ready to leave and forſake their Fathers Houſe, and to follow <hi>Jacob</hi> their Husband into his Country and Fathers Houſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.13, 14, 15, 16. Even ſo wilt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine to go forth to, and follow Chriſt to his Heavenly Country, if he be thy Husband, and the dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of thy Soul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 4. Have you caſt the Anchor of your hope within the Vail? <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.19, 20. Is your Treaſure and hope laid up in Heaven? <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.20. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.5. That way which our Anchor is caſt, our Souls will move: This is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; that a Chriſtian at the beginning of this Voyage, caſts his Anchor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Haven; and his whole Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age is but Sailing to the end of his Cable, and to the Poſſeſſion of that firm Land which his Anchor doth take hold of: Nothing will or can eſtabliſh you in the Storms that you you may meet with; but the hope of everlaſting life to be enjoyed in the inviſible World: This preſent world is as a rough Sea; Wicked Men hate, and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:54706:35"/>rage againſt the People of God: As ſome Seas are ſtill rough, and the Waves riſe and roul con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Scalig. Exercit.</hi> 58.</note> becauſe of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terraneous Winds that riſe into the Bowels of thoſe Seas. So the Men of this world are as a Sea that hath a Wind with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> Their Malice and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt the People of God; and therefore though no wind of injury or provocation blow on them from without, yet they cannot ceaſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligning and Perſecuting the people of God with their Hands or with their Tongues. And we ſhall never ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out on this rough and rouling Sea, if we have not caſt the Anchor of our hope within the Vail; and by it taken hold of Jeſus, as our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner into Glory: Sinful ſelf-love will lay an Imbargo on us, and keep us within the Port and Camp of the worlds friendſhip, if we do not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee and faſten on ſomething in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, which will countervail all the Dammage, and recompenſe all the Loſſes that we ſuſtain here: If
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54706:36"/>our All lay here below, we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver go out from our Treaſure, our Portion, and our Feaſt: Men will never conſent to be totally deſtroy'd; if they have not a new Intereſt in, and Title to another world, they will cleave to this preſent World: Have you therefore provided Bread, that the world knows not of; Bags they cannot riſle or take away; an Inheritance they cannot reach or rob you of? <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. <hi>They took joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully the ſpoiling of their Goods, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within themſelves, that in Heaven they had a more enduring ſubſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The third <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe is for Exhortation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 3. Is it the Duty of Chriſtians to go forth without the Camp to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus? Then I would preſs you to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with, and the Practice of this Duty: O! go forth to Jeſus; own, confeſs, and adhere unto him. This Exhortation I would urge and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force with ſeveral Motives. And then, Secondly, lay down ſeveral Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections how you may be enabled thus
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:54706:36"/>to go forth to Jeſus. Firſt, I ſhall lay down Motives to this Duty.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Motive.</hi> Conſider who Jeſus is, how great and Glorious a Perſon he is: He is Styled Jeſus the Son of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Having a great high Prieſt that is paſſed into the Heavens, Jeſus the Son of God, let us hold faſt our Profeſſion.</hi> Shall we draw back from, or be aſhamed of the Son of God? Shall the vain ſhews and paſſing Pageantry of this World, out-ſhine in our Eyes, and darken the Glory of the Son of God? He is the ſelf-exiſtent, and ſelf-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Eternal Jehovah; his Name is <hi>I am, Exod.</hi> 3.14. And this <hi>I am,</hi> ſhould annihilate all the things of this World in our eſteem and account. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.5. <hi>Wilt thou ſet thy Eyes on that which is not?</hi> Shall that which is not allure and draw our Hearts from <hi>I am?</hi> As the Sun obſcures and hides the Stars, ſo this Son of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>which is the brightneſs of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Glory, and the expreſs Image of his Perſon,</hi> Heb. 1.3. ſhould vail and darken all Creature-Beauty and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency: Shall ſuch vile Worms as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54706:37"/>the Sons of men be dreaded or loved more than the Almighty and bleſſed Son of God? Will you withdraw from him, and caſt him off, to ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate your ſelves with poor and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly Creatures? This is as if a man ſhould turn his back on the full Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer of a Rich and mighty King, and betake himſelf to an Alms-Houſe, God the Father poſſeſſed this Son of his (that is called Wiſdom) from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.22. He Poſſeſſed him as a Rich Treaſure, and a Spring of Eternal Delights: And this ſeems by far a more Glorious Title; That he is the Poſſeſſour of ſuch a Son; than that he is the Poſſeſſour of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.22. And doth the Father Glory in ſuch a Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion; and ſhall not we to cleave to, and hold faſt this bleſſed Son of God? Is he not able to do more for us, and will he not be better to us than the whole World? However Men revile and abhor him, he is glorious in the Eyes of God, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 49.5.7. And ſhall he not be precious in our Eyes? To you that believe he is precious, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:54706:37"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Motive.</hi> You cannot be ſincere Chriſtians if you go not out to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt, and prefer him not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the whole World: The very truth of ſaving grace lies in this, to wit, in our eſteeming and regarding Chriſt more than all things elſe: We muſt remember him and his Love, ſo as to forget all things elſe in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4. <hi>We will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy love more than Wine, we will be glad and rejoyce in thee.</hi> And how is Chriſt to be remembred? We do not rightly remember him, if we do not forget our People and Fathers Houſe for him, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 45.10. And ſo ſeek all our comfort, contentment, and ſatisfaction in him: We muſt ſo eſteem Chriſt, as utterly to deſpiſe whatever comes in competition with him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.7. <hi>If a Man would give all the ſubſtance of his Houſe for Love, it would be utterly deſpiſed.</hi> O! how ſhould we diſdain whatever is offered to buy our love off from Chriſt; or would ſubſtitute it ſelf as a beloved in his room and ſtead: all things ſhould be accounted but Dung for Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:54706:38"/>And ſo muſt we love Jeſus Chriſt, as to hate other things in compariſon of our tranſcendent love to Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.25, 26. So Chriſt teaches us, <hi>that if any Man will come after him, he muſt hate Father and Mother, Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Houſe and Lands, yea and his own life too; or elſe he cannot be his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> As <hi>Jacob</hi> is ſaid to hate <hi>Leah,</hi> and to love <hi>Rachel, Gen.</hi> 29.30, 31. becauſe <hi>Leah</hi> had but a little pittance in compariſon of <hi>Rachels</hi> greater Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of love: So we muſt love Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Life ſo little in reſpect of Chriſt, that we may truly be ſaid to hate them, and love him; and in an hour of temptation, we muſt as readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly part with them, as with hated things: He that loveth Father or Mother, Son or Daughter, more than Chriſt, is not worthy of him: We muſt ſo cleave to the Lord, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.23. as to forſake and caſt away all other things for him, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.33. <hi>Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he be, he that forſaketh not all that he hath, cannot be my Diſciple.</hi> Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial is the true ſavour of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; and without this, a Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:54706:38"/>Chriſtian is as Salt that hath loſt its ſavour, and is good for nothing, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.34, 35. <hi>He that taketh not up his Croſs and followeth Chriſt, is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of him,</hi> Matt. 10.38. If ever you will approve your ſelves true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, you muſt be ready to leave the Camp and go out to Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Mot.</hi> Conſider what will earthly Comforts avail or advantage thee without Chriſt: If thou forſake him, and cleave to them, they will prove a Curſe unto thee. O! how hurtful and pernicious is that to our Souls, that entices and draws us from the Son of God, (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9.) and as a Weight doth plunge us and ſink us down into perdition and deſtruction: The luſts of men after theſe things, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, do immerſe and drown Souls in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: Theſe earthly things are as a Weight that do preſs down a Racer, and hinder him from running his Courſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. It is the cares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, or the inordinate enjoyment of theſe things that overcharge the hearts of men, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.34. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, leſt your hearts be as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:54706:39"/>a Ship too hard or deep Loaden, that therefore is in danger to founder and ſink down in the Sea; and cannot well make way in its Courſe. Are not thoſe things miſchievous to us, that hinder us in our Race, and that obſtruct us in our Voyage towards the Haven of a Bleſſed Eternity? It is ſaid, <hi>the proſperity of Fools ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them,</hi> Prov. 1.32. They are Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that turn away from Chriſt to any Creature; and though they ſeem to flouriſh for a time in the World, yet their Plenty feeds and fuels their luſts, and ſo helps forward their ruine and deſtruction. Thus their Table proves a Snare to them, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 69.22. and by all their Proſperity they are but Fatted for the Slaughter, and more fitted for Deſtruction. Can the enjoyment of any of theſe things countervail the loſs of Jeſus Chriſt; or be a ſutable Portion to us in the room of Jeſus Chriſt? How eaſily can God imbitter all theſe things to us; and make us ſick and weary of them? <hi>Judas</hi> could take no pleaſure in the Pieces of Silver for which he ſold
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:54706:39"/>Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.34. <hi>Francis Spira</hi> could not endure to look on his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for the love of which he had denied the Truth of Chriſt;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>vid. Hiſt. of</hi> Spira.</note> he could not abide to eat any thing, ſo weary was he of life; all he took was forced as it were upon him: A wounded Spirit who can bear! The Favour of Princes will not bind up broken Hearts, or ſet broken Bones, or heal wounded Spirits. An Apoſtate may ſuffer more in one Nights Horrours, for denying Jeſus Chriſt; than a ſincere Chriſtian endures in many days Torments, for owning and confeſſing him: Account therefore, nothing can be either ſafe or ſweet to you, which is the Hire of an Harlot, or the Wages of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; I mean that you enjoy as the reward of your Treachery to Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Mot.</hi> If you go forth without the Camp, if you are caſt out as Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Lepers in the Worlds Eye; or are led out as Malefactors to Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you are but treated as your Head Lord and Maſter was; and are you better than he? <hi>Marvel not,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:54706:40"/>(ſaith Chriſt) <hi>If the World hate you, for it hated me before it hated you,</hi> John 15.18. It called the Maſter of the Houſe <hi>Belzebub;</hi> and will it begin to Honour, or ceaſe from reviling his Servants? <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.24, 25. You are not above Chriſt, or are to expect better uſage than he had. The world was a Wilderneſs to him; and ſhall it be a Paradiſe to us? He received here his Evil things, and ſhall we expect our Good things on this Earth? Is it fit that Members ſhould lead a pleaſant and delicious life under a Head Crowned with Thorns? Did the World caſt out Chriſt, and will it take us in? if it excerciſed ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Hoſpitality towards the Son of God; will it open its Doors to us?</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Mot.</hi> If by going forth to Jeſus, you expoſe your ſelves to Temporal Evils, yet he will be a ſhelter to you from greater and worſer Evils, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 32.2. a covert from the Wind, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge and hiding-place from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt of the Wrath of God: Though you may be the worlds Butts to be ſhot at, yet you ſhall not be Gods Mark;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:54706:40"/>Chriſt will be your Shield to guard you from the Eternal Arrows of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Vengeance: He is a Rain-bow round about the Throne, that Storms ſhall not fall from Heaven to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm you, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.3. He is a Prieſt on his Throne, a Mediator at the Right Hand of God, to maintain your Peace with Heaven; and to deliver you from the Wrath that is to come. You ſhall not be Food to the Worm that never dies; nor fuel to the Flames that ſhall never go out. The Blood of this Paſchal Lamb is ſprinkled on Believers, to keep deſtroying Juſtice out: Though the world draw upon you; yet the Sword of God is for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſheathed towards you: Though men caſt you out, Chriſt will ſeek you out and take you in: God your great Creditor will not arreſt and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you, and Conſcience ſhall not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and condemn you; for you are ſprinkled from an Evil Conſcience by the Blood of Chriſt; though winds do blow high without, yet there ſhall not be a Storm and dreadful Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, or rather Heart-quake, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:54706:41"/>in. It is worſe to be caſt as unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury Salt out of the Houſe of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. <hi>laſt.</hi> than for our conſtancy and faithfulneſs to Chriſt, to be thruſt out of the Camp of men; and this greater Evil Chriſt frees from: For the Sons of God ſhall abide in his Houſe for ever, <hi>John</hi> 8.35.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Mot.</hi> When you are called to go forth of the Camp to Jeſus, what are you required to leave, but what you are already dead to, if you are true Chriſtians? <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3. <hi>For you are dead, and your life is hid with Chriſt in God.</hi> In Chriſt Believers are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready dead to the Natural life that flows from the firſt <hi>Adam.</hi> This life Chriſt hath laid down, extinguiſhed and aboliſhed for ever in himſelf: He is riſen again to a more Excellent, Higher, and Nobler Life; and this Believers ſhould repute, reckon, and eſteem as their Life. The Apoſtle intimates, that we ought not to regard the Natural life as our life, but to account that is our life which is hid with Chriſt in God; and that we are riſen with Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1. and ſo
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:54706:41"/>have the beginnings and firſt Fruits of this new and glorious life. Now what are all the Riches, Honours, and Pleaſures of the World, to a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or to a dead Man? Why ſhould we be ſo ſollicitous or anxiouſly care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful about a life, or the concerns of that life that is aboliſhed by Chriſt, and that we are dead to in Jeſus our Head? All the Delights and Comforts of this world, are but the Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dixes or Appurtenances of this life that is aboliſhed by Chriſt, and Saints are not to enjoy their Happineſs in the old life of the firſt, but in the new life of the ſecond <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Mot.</hi> By going out to Jeſus Chriſt without the Camp, we defend the Goſpel, ſtrengthen the Faith, and inflame the Hearts of others with love to, and zeal for Chriſt; and have the comfort of our own tryed and approved Graces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> We defend and confirm the Goſpel. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.7. the Apoſtle ſpeaks of his Bonds, as his defence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the Goſpel: O! What an Honour is this to be Chriſts Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:54706:42"/>and by our Sufferings to defend and confirm the Truth of the Goſpel? This is a rational Argument, and Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence offered to the Spectators of Saints Sufferings, that ſurely this is truth; and theſe men are fully ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and aſſured that it is ſo, elſe they would not thus ſpend their Blood, and lay down their lives for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> This ſtrengthens the Faith of others, and incourages them to take up the Croſs; and daunts the Hearts of Adverſaries. Hereby the Faith of the Saints is fortified, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of his being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered upon the Sacrifice and Service of the <hi>Phillipians</hi> Faith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, That is, If my Blood be poured out as a Drink-Offering to ſhadow the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of your Faith. He alludes to the Drink-Offerings of Wine, that were of Old added to Sacrifices, according to the Law of <hi>Moſes, Levit.</hi> 23.13, 18. The Sacrifice and Service of the Saints Faith, would be much advantaged by <hi>Pauls</hi> Martyrdom; how would his Blood water thoſe heavenly Truths that he had ſown among them, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:54706:42"/>make them take deeper root, and fructifie more abundantly. And <hi>Pauls</hi> Bonds incouraged and imboldened o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers without fear to publiſh the Goſpel, while they beheld his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and conſtancy, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.12, 13, 14. The ſparks that have flown from the Flames of Suffering and Martyred Saints, have taken hold of the hearts of Spectators, and have fired them with love to Chriſt, and Zeal for his Glory. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> profeſſes, that he was much influenced and wrought upon, by the courage and joy of ſuffering and dying Chriſtians. And hereby often the Hearts of Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are quailed and diſcouraged from proceeding in their Cruelty. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells, that when <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate commanded the Chriſtians at <hi>Antioch</hi> to remove the Body of <hi>Babylas,</hi> they fell a ſinging the 114th <hi>Pſalm;</hi> at which the Emperour being inraged, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Saluſtius</hi> his Captain to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend ſome of them: Who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly took ſeveral Chriſtians; and among them one <hi>Theodorus,</hi> a Young man, whom he cauſed to be Torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:54706:43"/>for ſeveral Hours, yet he ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſinging the 114th <hi>Pſalm:</hi> At which <hi>Saluſtius</hi> was ſo diſmaid, that he cauſed the Tormentors to ceaſe; and went to the Emperour, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him that no more might be Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, for all the Chriſtian Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing did but tend to their Glory: By whom the Emperour was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to torture no more of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians at <hi>Antioch,</hi> whom he had ſeized upon.</p>
            <p>And hereby <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of their tried and approved Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: The Apoſtle ſalutes <hi>Apelles</hi> as one <hi>approved in Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 16.10. O! what a mark of Honour is it for a man in ſignal ſervices and eminent ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to be approved as ſincere in <hi>Chriſt?</hi> A tryed Faith is a precious Faith, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. O! how comfortable is it for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to ſay, This Faith hath been in the Furnace, this Love hath paſſed through a Fiery Tryal, and hath not ſailed or abated? <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath been evidenced to be dearer to me than all the world?</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Mot.</hi> If we go forth to Jeſus, we
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:54706:43"/>ſhall be no loſers by it: A viſit from Chriſt will make a Priſon better than a Palace; <hi>He will not leave you comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, he will come to you, John</hi> 14.18. When you are thruſt out of the worlds <hi>Camp,</hi> and ſeem as naked men in the open field, yet then the Power of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall reſt upon you, and as a Tent over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadow you, as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, uſed by the Apoſtle, doth import, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. If your ſufferings do abound, your conſolations by <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall abound much more, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4. When all men forſake you, the Lord will ſtand with you and for you, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.17. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you leave and forſake for <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel</hi>'s ſake, ſhall be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed to you an hundred fold, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.28, 29. and that <hi>now in this time,</hi> as it is expreſſed, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.30. and that with Perſecutions, as is further intimated; though the world rage, and perſecute the people of God, yet theſe Perſecutions ſhall not fruſtrate, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, the performance of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
            <p>But how ſhall the Promiſe be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled?</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:54706:44"/>
            <p>I anſwer, In a double ſenſe it is made good.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe that forſake their Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons according to the Fleſh, ſhall have the Favour and Friendſhip of a new Kindred according to the Spirit; and there is nothing like to <hi>Love in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Col.</hi> 1.8. Love on a Spiritual ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count is the Pureſt and Nobleſt Flame, an Eternal Fire, that ſhall never be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed. You that leave Parents, Brethren, Siſters, Kinſmen, that are related to you in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> you ſhall have a new Stock of Kindred, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to you in the ſecond <hi>Adam.</hi> El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſtians ſhall expreſs the kindneſs of Fathers and Mothers, and younger Saints ſhall manifeſt the love of Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Siſters; and ſo you ſhall have a hundred Spiritual Kinſmen for one Natural Kinſman that you loſe. Chriſt deſigns to joyn and link Men of ſeveral Nations in the neareſt, beſt, and ſtrongeſt Bonds; and to gather ſome of all Nations into one Family and <hi>houſhold of Faith, Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.19. and thereby to kindle the moſt admirable and excellent Love
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:54706:44"/>among the Members of this New Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: And thoſe that forſake Houſe and Lands, ſhall have the Hearts, Houſes, and Purſes of their Spiritual Kindred opened to them, to receive their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſupply their Neceſſities: and this will the more incline and ſway them to extend ſuch Kindneſs, becauſe they account they exerciſe Hoſpitality to Chriſt, they take him in, feed and cloath him in his Members.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suffering Saints receive a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred-fold now in the preſent time, as they experience the ſmalleſt Portion and Pittance of outward things that they enjoy, to be a hundred-fold better than the greater Plenty and Abundance of the Wicked, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.16. <hi>A little that a righteous man hath, is better than the riches of many wicked.</hi> And why is it better? Surely this is that which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hances and advances the value and worth of what the Righteous have, that it flows from the Love of God as a Father; that it is caſt in as an Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>Kingdom of God and his Righteouſneſs, Matth.</hi> 6.33. that <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hath not onely the promiſes of this
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:54706:45"/>Life, but of that which is to come,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. that as <hi>God's Firſt-born, Heb.</hi> 12.23. they have the double Portion, Proviſion on their way, and the Eternal Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance at the Journeys end: God breeds, feeds, and maintains them in their Minority, and hath laid up great Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for them in Heaven; there <hi>a Crown is laid up,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>an Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is reſerved,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>a Reſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains for them, Heb.</hi> 4.9. While their Bodies feed on God's Creatures, their Souls may delight in, and feaſt on their Fathers Love; accounting, that <hi>he gives bread to them that fear him, he will ever be mindful of his Covenant, Pſal.</hi> 111.5. that he <hi>ſpreads their Table, fills their Cup,</hi> Pſal. 23.5. <hi>annoints their heads</hi> and hearts with Oyl of Joy; as Ointment was poured on great and noble Gueſts, when they were entertained at a Feaſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.7. They take all as coming immediately from God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.15. <hi>The God that fed me all my life long.</hi> He looks beyond <hi>Joſeph, Egypt,</hi> and all Creatures; he aſcends to God: as the Prieſts had the Lord for their Portion, he provided and gave main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:54706:45"/>to them; the Altar was as it were their Field, from whence they had Bread and Fleſh, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.22. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what was brought to, and laid on it, is called <hi>the Fruits of it,</hi> as if it grew there for the Prieſts, that had their Portion of the Sacrifices, and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid <hi>to live upon holy things, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with the Altar,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.13. Even ſo God is the Portion of his People, even in Temporal as well as Spiritual reſpects, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.5. <hi>The Lord is the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my inheritance, and of my cup.</hi> Their very outward Enjoyments are as <hi>Shew-bread,</hi> or <hi>Face-bread,</hi> as it is in the Original, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.30. They receive them as thoſe Loaves of Shew-bread from the Face of God; they ſee his Face and Love in them, and therefore may call them <hi>Peniel, Gen.</hi> 32.30. They take their daily Proviſion as a Diſh ſent from their Father's Table; as <hi>Joſeph</hi> is ſaid to ſend Meſſes from before him to his Brethren, <hi>Gen.</hi> 43. <hi>laſt.</hi> Their Food is ſeaſoned with the ſenſe of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Love, and with the hope of his Kingdom and Glory; and ſo their Sawee is better than their Meat. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:54706:46"/>after this Hundred-fold in the preſent time, they are to inherit Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He that loſeth his life ſhall find it; but he that finds it, ſhall loſe it, Mat.</hi> 10.39. <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>Died Abner as a fool?</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.33. So I may ſay, Do Saints die as Fools? Do they laviſh out their Blood, and raſhly ſquander away their Lives? Surely no; they well underſtand them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and know what they do; if they loſe their Lives for Chriſt, they ſhall find a better Life for their very Bodies. They lay down the vile common Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beian Life of the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> but they ſhall at the Reſurrection receive and take up the Honourable, Royal, and Glorious Life of the ſecond <hi>Adam, Phil.</hi> 3.21. <hi>He ſhall faſhion our vile Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies like his glorious Body. If we be faithful to the death, we ſhall receive from Chriſt the Crown of Life, Rev.</hi> 2.10. Mark that Expreſſion, <hi>[The Crown of Life.]</hi> This very <hi>Life</hi> is <hi>a Crown;</hi> it is a Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Life. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17. it is ſaid, <hi>That they that receive an abundance of grace, and of the gift of righteouſneſs, ſhall reign in life,</hi> So that Saints loſe a baſe and common
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:54706:46"/>Life, and are recompenſed with a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Life. All Vails ſhall be taken off, all Clouds ſhall be ſcattered, all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches ſhall be wiped away from the Saints; <hi>the righteous ſhall ſhine out in the kingdom of their father, Matth.</hi> 13.43.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as the Sun, that diſperſes all Clouds.</note> But <hi>thoſe that reſolve to ſave their lives ſhall loſe them.</hi> This is certain, that by a fond and ſinful ſparing of their Lives here, they ſhall cut themſelves off from all the Glory and Bleſſedneſs that Saints ſhall enjoy in their Souls and Bodies: Hereafter they ſhall only Be, to be Miſerable; and be continued, to endure the Blows of an Almighty Arm, to drink the Wine of the Wrath of an Eternal God; and this is but a Husk and Carcaſe of Being, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. <hi>laſt,</hi> to be preſerved to be Fuel of Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Flames: This State of the Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked therefore is not called <hi>Life,</hi> but <hi>the ſecond Death;</hi> yea, ſometimes in this Life Apoſtates meet with remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and infamous puniſhment, and quickly loſe that Life that ſinfully they preſerved. He in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:54706:47"/>that ſaid,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Foxes</hi> Acts &amp; Monuments.</note> 
               <hi>he could not burn for the Goſpel,</hi> (of which in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Days he had been a forward Profeſſor) was himſelf, and all his Houſe and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, burnt in the Night, by a Fire that roſe ſuddenly: And the Prieſt that denied the Truth in <hi>France</hi> to ſave his Life, and was diſcharged out of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as he was going home met with two Men that had a quarrel with him for merly, who fell upon him, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him. <hi>See</hi> Clarke<hi>'s Hiſtory of the French Martyrs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall now lay down ſome Directions how you may attain ſuch a frame of Spirit as will incline you rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and freely to <hi>go forth without the Camp to Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Direction</hi> 1. Endeavour to get a clear ſight of the Shortneſs of Life, and the Vanity of all the Things of this World. <hi>Surely every man walks in a vain ſhew, Pſal.</hi> 39.6. What is this <hi>vain ſhew?</hi> I anſwer, It is the Natural Life, and the earneſt and reſtleſs Endeavours of Men about it, and for it. This Life is but a vain ſhew of Life, as a Shadow
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:54706:47"/>that hath the ſhape of Man's Body, but yet is but a vain ſhew of a Body, or a Picture that hath the reſemblance of a Man, of his Head, Face, Body, Hands, and Feet; but come to handle it, there is nothing but Canvas and Colours; there is only a vain ſhew of a Man, and of his Members, but no Fleſh, Bones, or Life. So this preſent Life is but a Shadow, a vain ſhew of that true and real Life that flows from Jeſus Chriſt, and is to be enjoyed for ever with him. And all the Labours and Toil of Men, to provide for and maintain this Life, is but a vain ſhew of Buſineſs: Men ſeem to do ſomething, but indeed do nothing to purpoſe, as long as they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect theit Souls: It is a buſie Idleneſs, a laborious doing of nothing; juſt like Children that make Pies, build Houſes, dreſs Babies, and talk over every piece of their Work, as if it were ſome very ſerious weighty thing; and all is but a piece of childiſh Folly and Vanity. When God awakes to judge the World, how will he himſelf deſpiſe, and render moſt ridiculous and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible to others, this <hi>Image of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:54706:48"/>men? Pſal.</hi> 73.20. How will he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride their Folly, that forget their Souls, caſt God and his Word behind their backs, baniſh the Thoughts of Eternity out of their Minds, and ſatisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſuch a vile Life, and ſuch a vain Image of Happineſs? And the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> in this 39 <hi>Pſalm, ver.</hi> 6. ſaith, That a worldly Man <hi>heaps up Riches, and knows not who ſhall gather them.</hi> He ſeems to allude to the Cuſtom of ſome Countries, where the Corn is heaped up, and ſet Artificially in the Field, ſo as to preſerve it from Weather, till all their Harveſt is cut, and then they ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it all into the Barn: and in this Expreſſion he ſhews the ſhortneſs and uncertainty of Life; when one Man hath plowed, ſowed, reaped, heaped up in the Field, and is near the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Fruit of his Labours, his Soul is ſuddenly required, his Life va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth, and another gathers into the Barn, and enjoys what he had toiled for. The Holy Ghoſt calls it but <hi>the faſhion of this world,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31. <hi>The faſhion of this world paſſeth away.</hi> Some conceive it is an Alluſion to a Comedy,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:54706:48"/>in which one acts the part of a Buyer, another of a Lover that wooes and marries, and another of a Mourner; but all this is a vain ſhew, it is but a perſonating Men and their Actions; there is nothing of this that is True and Real, but all is Fiction and Imagery. The Affections of the Actors do not anſwer to their Actions: So ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29, 30. <hi>They that have Wives, ſhould be as if they had none; thoſe that buy, as if they poſſeſſed not; thoſe that weep, as if they wept not; and they that rejoyce, as if they rejoyced not.</hi> And why ſhould Chriſtians be ſo much unconcerned about the Things of this Life? The Apoſtle renders the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in <hi>ver.</hi> 31. <hi>For the faſhion of this world paſſeth away.</hi> All is but a Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, a vain ſhew; and therefore perſons ſhould not earneſtly let out their Thoughts, or lay out their Affections on the things of this World. Man is ſaid to <hi>fly away as a ſhadow, Job</hi> 14.2. and Riches are ſaid to <hi>fly away as an eagle towards heaven, Prov.</hi> 23.5. And both Expreſſions do ſet forth the Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Life and Worldly Enjoyments.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:54706:49"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Direction</hi> 2. Endeavour to ſee and ſeriouſly to believe the miſery of all thoſe that have <hi>their portion in this life, Pſal.</hi> 17.14. <hi>David</hi> deſired to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from thoſe that were <hi>men of this world,</hi> and had their All here; he dreads to have his Lot among ſuch, he would not <hi>eat of their dainties, Pſal.</hi> 141.4. Their Bellies were indeed full of the choiceſt, rareſt, and beſt Dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Creature (which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> calls <hi>God's hid treaſure,</hi> becauſe thoſe things are not common, ordinary, or every where to be found) but here is no mention of any Food or Furniture for their Souls. <hi>The Kings Daughter is all glorious within, Pſal.</hi> 45.13. and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>the joy that God put into his heart by the light of his countenance, Pſal.</hi> 4, 6, 7. It is ſpoken of as a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſin to <hi>mind earthly things, Phil.</hi> 3.19. and it is threatned as a ſore puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Men to have their <hi>names writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the earth, Jer.</hi> 17.13. They that are written in the Earth, how ſoon may their Names be blotted out, and their Happineſs deſtroyed? But it is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of higheſt comfort and joy to have
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:54706:49"/>our Names written in Heaven, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.20. <hi>Rejoyce in this, that your Names are written in Heaven.</hi> The Wind, or the Foot of the next Traveller, may blot out a Name written in Duſt; but who can or ſhall aſcend and blot out a Name written in Heaven? How are Men debaſed that ſet their Hearts on things below? How diſgraceful is it, to be called onely Men of this World, Men of this Earth, Children of this World, ſtooping and bowed down wholly to theſe preſent and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing things? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.8. And how woful is their State that receive their Reward, their Conſolation, their Good things here? <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.2. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.24. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.25. But when Death comes, their Candle is quite put out; they have no happy Reward after Death! they ſhall never ſee the Light, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.19. They ſhall inherit nothing but Beggary and Poverty, Torments and Miſery, in another World. This World is the Baſtards Portion, but Heaven is the Childrens Inheritance. As Satan with the Fruit of a Tree deprived our firſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:54706:50"/>Parents of the earthly, ſo Satan with the Trifles of this World cheats earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men, and bereaves them of the Heavenly Paradiſe. As the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> laboured onely for preſent Meat and Drink, they had no Wages from the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> ſo Worldly Men toil onely for preſent Proviſions and Enjoyments, <hi>they ſhall have no reward, Prov.</hi> 24.20. As <hi>Iſmael</hi> was turned out of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Houſe with a few Loaves of Bread and Bottle of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and was not to be Heir with <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 21.10, 14. even ſo the Men of this World ſhall be thruſt and excluded out of God's Houſe, and be put off onely with preſent and temporal things; but ſhall not be Heirs with <hi>the Saints in Light.</hi> And ſhall we ſtay with ſuch <hi>in the Camp?</hi> Is it not better to ſuffer from them, than to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and periſh for ever with them? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.32. <hi>Though the wicked ſpring as the graſs, and all the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity do flouriſh here, yet they ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for ever, Pſal.</hi> 92.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Direction</hi> 3. We muſt overcome and be Crucified to the World, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:54706:50"/>
               <hi>The World is Crucified to me, and I am Crucified to it,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul).</hi> If the world be as a dead Carcaſe to us, and we are as dead Carcaſſes to it; it will be no hard thing to ſeparate and part two ſuch dead Carcaſſes, they cannot cling to, and embrace each other: If the world be Crucified to us, that is be laid low in our eſteem and judgments; then we ſhall be Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to it, that is our affections will die to it: <hi>He that is Born of God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercometh the World,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.4, 5. If men be not born of God, have not a higher Nature, and better life than others, there will be neither Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Souldiers, or Weapons to fight againſt, and overcome the World: The new Nature inclines men to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and raiſes them up to higher Riches, Honours, and Pleaſures, than thoſe that are the Objects of Senſe. Worldly luſts come to be ſtarved, by the Souls ſight of, and longing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heavenly enjoyments: And the more theſe are prized, and purſued, the more a Chriſtian is weaned from all things below: And keeps a Spiritual
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:54706:51"/>Faſt, ſomething like Chriſts Faſt in the Wilderneſs, who for Forty days did not only abſtain from eating, but did not hunger after Food, <hi>Matt.</hi> 4.2. For it was at the end of Forty days that he was an hungry. So this is that Excellent Faſt that we ſhould aſpire to; not to eſteem, hunger, or luſt after the things of this World: Grace teaches to deny worldly luſts, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12, 13. As Pilgrims and Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers we are to abſtain from Fleſhly luſts, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. If the world live in our Hearts, if our Affections cleave to it, it will be a meer force, an Act of Violence to tear us from what we embrace and delight in as our Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs: Thus it was with the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites;</hi> they came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as to bodily ſeparation from it, but they brought <hi>Egypt</hi> out in their Hearts; they had Pleaſant and Delightful thoughts of <hi>Egypt;</hi> with Complacency they call to mind the Fleſh-Pots of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the fullneſs of Bread they had there, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.3. And in the 11. of <hi>Numb.</hi> the 5. <hi>Verſe. We remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Fiſh which we did eat in</hi> Egypt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:54706:51"/>
               <hi>freely; the Cucumbers, the Melons, the Leeks, the Onions, and the Garlick:</hi> There they accounted they had their Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties, Fiſh and Fleſh; ſeveral ſorts of Sallets and Fruits; but now they reckoned they were at ſhort Commons, and confined to one Diſh, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>There is nothing but this Manna before our Eyes:</hi> And their Soul was dried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with it. And <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.13. Some of them chid with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge him for bringing them up out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which they call, <hi>a Land flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Milk and Honey:</hi> O! how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, pleaſant a Land is <hi>Egypt</hi> in their Eye! The <hi>Epithetes</hi> God gave to <hi>Canaan,</hi> they transfer and apply to <hi>Egypt,</hi> as if the Country they were called from, did better deſerve this Name than the Land that they were called to: And they ſeemed ſo far to be tranſported with the love of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and to repent of their leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, that they ſtirred up one another to make a Captain, and to return thither again: And <hi>Stephen</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, that they returned to <hi>Egypt</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in their Hearts, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.39. Thus
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:54706:52"/>too many pretend a ſeparation from the World, yet the World is ſtill in their Hearts: And while it is thus, they will never go forth without the Camp to Jeſus. But Chriſtians ſhould ſtrive to imitate <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob:</hi> The Scripture ſaith, <hi>that if they had been mindful of the Country from whence they came out; they might have had opportunity to have returned,</hi> Heb. 11.15. Hereby the Divine Pen-man ſufficiently intimates, that they were not mindful of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r</hi> of the <hi>Chaldees,</hi> the Country from whence <hi>Abraham</hi> came. They did not confeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Pilgrims and Strangers, becauſe drawn from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r;</hi> but becauſe they were yet on Earth, and not arrived in Heaven: They were quite weaned from, and dead to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r,</hi> and all other Countries on Earth. Thus the world ſhould be rooted and baniſhed out of our Minds and Hearts. <hi>Chriſt hath choſen his people out of the World,</hi> John 15.19. and therefore they ſhould not remember or be enticed by it, but leave this Camp, and go forth to Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Direct.</hi> Labour to get a clear ſight
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:54706:52"/>and deep ſenſe of the love of Chriſt to periſhing Sinners; and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to your own Souls. How won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful is it that He that made all things ſhould be made Fleſh, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.2.14. that the Creator ſhould become a Creature: That the Fountain and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean of Being ſhould take a Humane Nature; and ſo become a drop of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. A Diamond or Ruby is deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed when ſet in Iron or Lead; what a wonderful condeſcention is it then, that the Divine Nature ſhould be joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Humane Nature in the Perſon of the Son? <hi>How did he that was in the Form of God, and thought it no Robbery to be equal with God;</hi> empty and humble himſelf, by becoming man. They are very Excellent and Empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Words that the Apoſtle uſes, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he emptied himſelf of all Majeſty, State, and Divine Glory in the Eye of Man, which the Apoſtle admirably expreſſes thus, <hi>He was found in Faſhion like a Man:</hi> That is, he looked but like an ordinary and common Man, as if there were nothing extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:54706:53"/>or ſupernatural in him, as if he were no more than a Man. Thus he vailed his Eternity, Omnipotency, Immenſity, and infinite Wiſdom; by becoming an Infant of Days, a Weak Child, confined to a Manger or a Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and not able for the preſent to ſpeak and expreſs the inward Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Soul: The Ancient of Days, yea he that was Ancienter than Days; whoſe goings forth were from Everlaſting, came forth of <hi>Bethlem</hi> but yeſterday! <hi>Mic.</hi> 5.2. All Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Benefits are compared by <hi>Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſienſis</hi> to ſparks of Fire: But when Jeſus Chriſt came into the World, this he ſaith was a Mountain of Fire caſt into the Earth: How ſhould the Hearts of the Sons of Men be inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this wonderful and aſtoniſhing kindneſs of God, in ſending his Son? And Chriſt did not ſtop here, but he ſtooped yet lower, when he was he found in faſhion of an ordinary common Man; he humbled himſelf to death; and that not an ordinary or common one, but to the death of the Croſs: A death that Servants, Thieves,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:54706:53"/>and the worſt of Malefactors were adjudged to: A painful, lingring, and moſt ſhameful death it was; and this he did undergo that Sinners might not Periſh Everlaſtingly: He that was the Judge, and might have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed Offenders; O! that he ſhould ſtand and ſuffer as an Offender! He that might have Executed Vengeance on us, did endure it for us: He (to whoſe Juſtice we might have been offered up as whole burnt-Offerings in Everlaſting Flames) became a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice himſelf. Needed the Father or the Son to have valued the loſs and ruine of a world of Sinners? What are all Nations to God, <hi>but as the drop of a Bucket, and as the ſmall Duſt that cleaves to the Ballance,</hi> Iſ. 40.15. And who values the loſs of a drop of Water, or of a mote of Duſt? And as unconcerned might God have been at the loſs of the whole World; but the Bowels of the Son of God yearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards a periſhing World; and rather than the Sheep ſhould go to the Slaughter, the Shepherd offers himſelf to be their Ranſom and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:54706:54"/>And how reſolved was Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to perfect this work, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 50.6, 7. <hi>He gave his Back to the Smi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, his Cheeks to thoſe that plucked off the Hair: He hid not his Face from Shame and Spitting; he ſet his Face as a Flint.</hi> This expreſſion may be illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and commented on by the words of <hi>Luke, Luke</hi> 9.51. In <hi>Iſaiah</hi> we have the Propheſie, in <hi>Luke</hi> the Hiſtory of Chriſt. <hi>He ſtedfaſtly ſet his Face to go up to</hi> Jeruſalem, (ſaith <hi>Luke.) He ſet his Face as a Flint,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iſaiah.</hi>) Chriſt was reſolved to go through the Storm; he knew what a dreadful Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt did abide him at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> yet he would not recoil, draw back, or turn his Face from it. He was as ſtedfaſt, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, as if his Face had been a Flint, and without ſenſe or feeling of Pain and anguiſh, of Blows and Wounds: Again it is ſaid, <hi>he poured out his Soul to the death,</hi> Iſ. 53.12. How much love is implyed and imported in this Expreſſion, That Chriſt had as low and vile thoughts of his Life, and was as freely and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ready to part with it, as if he had but poured out ſo much Water on
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:54706:54"/>the ground. O! how bounteous and large Hearted was Chriſt, that he did not ſpare his very Blood! Love made him yet wiſely and holily prodigal of his Life, he poured out his Soul to the death.</p>
            <p>Chriſt's Adverſaries upbraided him thus, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.42. <hi>He ſaved others, but himſelf he cannot ſave.</hi> Theſe very Words of Chriſt's Enemies ſignifie and ſet out to us the wonderful Love and excellent Self-denial of Jeſus Chriſt. He wrought Miracles to heal the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of ſome, and he raiſed up others from the Dead; ſome he kept from preſently falling into the Hands, others he reſcued from the Jaws and Power of Death: And they thought, ſurely he that was ſo kind to others, would much more be prompted and induced by Self-love to ſave himſelf, if he could; and becauſe he did not deliver himſelf, they conclude he could not. How do they exult and triumph, as if his Power were dried up and gone, his mighty Arm withered or broken; as if his Relief and Help were confined to others, but he could extend no Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:54706:55"/>to himſelf: And why did not Chriſt then ſave himſelf? Surely it was in wonderful pity and kindneſs to Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that he would not ſave himſelf, till he had ſuffered and ſatisfied for them; and ſo could not onely ſave himſelf, but alſo ſave them too. O, how was Chriſt wholly ſwallowed up in Love to his Father and periſhing Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, when he prayed thus, <hi>Father, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thy own Name!</hi> John 12.27, 28. As if he ſhould ſay, Father, whatever become of me, whatever I ſuffer and endure, <hi>glorifie thy own Name,</hi> glorifie thy Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in puniſhing Sin, and ſo make way to glorifie thy Mercy. in pardoning Sinners. Meditate of theſe great Truths of the Goſpel; uſe them as a Spiritual Burning-glaſs, till thy Heart be enflamed towards Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Direction</hi> 5. We muſt have an high Eſteem and Value for Jeſus Chriſt; and our Hearts muſt burn with Love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt have an high Eſteem of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10. <hi>My beloved is white and ruddy, the chiefeſt of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands.</hi> White, as to the Purity of his
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:54706:55"/>Life; and Ruddy, in his Bloody Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Death, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.2. <hi>Thou art fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than the children of men, Grace is pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out into thy lips. Thy Name</hi> (ſaith the Church, Cant. 1.3.) <hi>is as an Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment poured out: All his garments ſmell of Myrrh, Aloes, and Caſſia,</hi> Pſalm 45.8. We muſt account Chriſt better than our People, and our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe: That it is our Intereſt to pleaſe him, though we diſguſt and diſpleaſe the whole World; and that it will be our advantage to cleave to him, though all men ſhould frown on us, be imbittered towards us, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged againſt us: <hi>His Love is better than Wine; and his Kindneſs better than Life,</hi> Cant. 1.4. Pſ. 63.3. Let all the world be put into the Ballance to weigh againſt Chriſt, it will be found to be lighter than Vanity; what is all we have to be eſteemed in regard of Chriſt? We muſt ſell all to buy the Pearl of Price, but we muſt not ſell this Pearl to buy Peace, Liberty, or a quiet enjoyment of our Eſtates in the World: If we come out from Wicked Men, God and Chriſt will
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54706:56"/>receive us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2 <hi>laſt Verſes.</hi> We ſhould little regard the Worlds rejecting of us, if Chriſt will receive us. Should a Man be grieved if he be turned out of the Cottage of a Beggar, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Palace of a King? As the King of <hi>Sodom</hi> ſaid to <hi>Abraham,</hi> give me the Perſons, and take thou the Goods to thy ſelf: So we ſhould ſay to Carnal men, take you the Goods of this world to your ſelves, but leave me the Perſon of Chriſt; and I ſhall account my Lines are fallen to me in Pleaſant Places, and I have a goodly Heritage.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. Our Hearts muſt Burn with love towards Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6, 7. <hi>Many Waters cannot quench love, neither can the Floods drown it:</hi> O ſuch a divine Flame of love ſhould be kindled in our Hearts, that if the World lets in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and turns over us Rivers of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Floods of ſufferings, yet all may not be able to quench it: If we thus love Jeſus Chriſt, we ſhall follow him. As <hi>Ruth</hi> ſaid to <hi>Naomi, Intreat me not to leave thee, or to return from following af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thee: For whither thou goeſt, I will
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:54706:56"/>go; and where thou lodgeſt I will lodge: thy People ſhall be my People, and thy God ſhall be my God: Ruth</hi> 1.16. So thoſe that love Chriſt will ſay to the World, Allure me not to leave Jeſus Chriſt, or to return from following of him, where he is, there will I be: his God ſhall be my God, his People ſhall be my People. As <hi>Peter</hi> was ſo in love with Chriſt, that he caſt himſelf into the Sea, that he might ſwim and come to Chriſt ſtanding on the Shoar, <hi>John</hi> 21.7. So Chriſtians that highly prize, and dearly love him, will be willing not only to come to Chriſt by a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural death (as other Diſciples came to Chriſt by their Boat or little Ship, <hi>John</hi> 21.8.) but to be caſt into a Sea of ſufferings, and ſo come to Chriſt by a violent Death. As <hi>Ignatius,</hi> an ancient Father, in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> expreſſes himſelf thus. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Let the Fire, the Croſs, the Wild Beaſts, and other Inſtruments of Cruelty come on me, onely that I may obtain and enjoy Chriſt.</hi> He cared not what he ſuffered or endured,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:54706:57"/>ſo that he might come to Chriſt: Love is ſaid to be ſtronger than Death; and Jealouſie is cruel as the Grave, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6. As Death kills the ſtrongeſt, and the Grave ſwallows up all the bodies put into it, and turns them into Duſt, ſo true ſervent love to Chriſt will ſubdue all oppoſition, Conquer all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and is Cruel to what would tempt or draw it from Chriſt: So did <hi>Paul</hi> love Chriſt, that he deſired to be diſſolved, to be taken to pieces, ſo that his Soul might be with Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Direct.</hi> We muſt eye and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently think upon the Examples of ſuffering Saints, who through Faith and Patience have inherited the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Kingdom and inheritance. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.36, 37, 38. there is a ſhort ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the various ſufferings of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the Lords Worthies, what loſſes they ſuſtained, what tortures they endured; that they might obtain a better Reſurrection, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35. yet the World to come, was not ſo much Unvailed and Revealed then, as it is now; well may the duty of ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:54706:57"/>and bearing the Croſs, be more explicitely required, and more often preſſed in the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.23, 24. when the motives and incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to it are more clearly and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly revealed. We ſee Death foiled and aboliſhed; a new Life ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and Heaven poſſeſſed by Chriſt as a fore-runner. Yet Saints of old ſupported their Hearts with the hope of a glorious Reſurrection, and this carried them through the greateſt loſſes, and the moſt exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: and their Example is impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Being compaſſed with ſuch a cloud of Witneſſes, let us run the Race that is ſet before us.</hi> There may perhaps be an alluſion to the Cloud that went before, and guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Wilderneſs, and directed them in the way to the Earthly <hi>Canaan:</hi> So we have a great Cloud of Spiritual Witneſſes, that have teſtified God's Truth, and their own Love and Loyalty to him, with their Blood; and ſhall not their Examples both guide and animate us to the ſame Faith and Patience as they pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed?
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:54706:58"/>Their ſufferings teach us, that the way to the Heavenly <hi>Canaan</hi> lyes through the Briars and Thorns of afflictions, and that through many Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, we muſt expect to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of God. We may learn from them, that it is poſſible for poor frail Men to overcome all the Rage and Cruelty of the World, that the greateſt Torments may be patiently endured, and that Chriſt can Ride Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant on ſuch poor Worms as we are; and by the weakeſt conquer all the ſtrength and power of the World. The ſame Spirit that animated and enabled them, is yet alive, to Cloath us with like Magnaminity and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the Captain of Salvation is the ſame; the Spiritual Weapons that we are to fight with, are the ſame; the promiſes of Spiritual ſupplies and ſupports are the ſame; why then ſhould Chriſtians now deſpond or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of like ſucceſs and victory? How many of the Primitive Saints did trend in their ſteps, deſpiſing Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and trampling on Death it ſelf?
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:54706:58"/>
               <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In dial. cum Tryph. Jude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> applies that of <hi>Micah.</hi> 4.4. to the Chriſtians of his time; he thus Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to the Enemies of the Church, ſaying, <hi>You behead us, burn us, and in ſeveral other ways kill us; but yet you cannot make us afraid, or deſtroy us:</hi> When the Devil raged in the <hi>Roman</hi> Heathen Emperour, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1.2, 3, 4. A great Red Dragon ſtanding before the Church, that was as a Woman in Travel, to devour her Man-Child, to deſtroy any Chriſtians as ſoon as they were Spiritually brought forth to Chriſt; yet this did not hinder Men from Embracing and Profeſſing Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, <hi>v.</hi> 11. but they overcame all the threatnings and cruelty of the World <hi>by the Blood of the Lamb, and the word of their Teſtimony, and they leved not their lives unto the death. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> ſaid of old, <hi>Nos Chriſtiani Spiritu magis viventes ſumus, quam Corpore:</hi> We Chriſtians do live rather in our Spirits than in our Bodies. They did eſtimate and value the life of their Better, and deſpiſe the life of their
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:54706:59"/>Baſer part. <hi>Arnobius contr. Gentes,</hi> tells the Heathen, You benefit and not hurt us by killing of us; our Souls are in our Bodies as in a dark Priſon, and by Martyring of us, you do but pull down the Walls of our Priſon, and let in the pure and comfortable light up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us. What a great Speech is that of <hi>Ignatius, in Epiſt. ad Rom:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Now being bound in Chriſt, I learn to deſire no worldly or vain thing.</hi> He intimates, he was weaned from, and dead to all things in this World. And doth not the ſame Spirit dwell and act in all the Saints of God? How then ſhould we truſt upon the ſame Spirit, for the ſame quickning, Courage, and Strength?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Direction</hi> 7. We muſt look beyond this World, and above our ill Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Uſage here. <hi>Faith ſees him that is inviſible,</hi> Heb. 11.27. and cauſes the Soul to look at <hi>the things that are not ſeen,</hi> 2 Cor. 4. laſt. Though Chriſt be withdrawn from the Eye of Senſe, and Heaven be behind the Vail, far remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Apprehenſions of the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:54706:59"/>Natural Man; yet Faith can pierce the Heavens, behold the Churches King there in his Glory, and ſee that goodly Heavenly <hi>Canaan</hi> that is afar off, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.17. If your Eye doth not go out of the World, your Hearts will not go beyond it; and if your Eye and Hearts do not paſs out of this World, you will never be willing to <hi>go without the Camp to Jeſus.</hi> It is Faith that muſt ſurvey that glorious City that is above, and make report of it to the Soul: It is the Belief of what is teſtified of it in the Scripture, that muſt animate the Soul to overcome all the Dangers and Difficulties that are in the way to it. You muſt liſten to what the Word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares concerning this excellent City. Glorious things are ſpoken of this Heavenly <hi>Zion,</hi> the City of our God. Chriſt mentions it as an excellent Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege, to have <hi>the Name of the City of his God</hi> to be written on any Man, and for him to be reputed <hi>a Citizen of the New Jeruſalem,</hi> Rev. 3.12. <hi>I will write upon him that overcomes the Name of the City of my God.</hi> There is no Temple, or need of the Light of the Sun or of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:54706:60"/>the Moon in this City; God is All here to his People, to their Souls without Ordinances, and to their Bodies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Creatures, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.22, 23. This is a moſt rich and ſelf-ſufficient City; it needs not Proviſions to be brought in from without, the Tree of Life grows in it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.1, 2. and a River of pure Living Water iſſues from the Throne of God and of the Lamb. The Fruit of this Tree of Life, and this River of Living Water, will make a delicious and eternal Feaſt to all the Inhabitants of this Bleſſed City. Look for this <hi>abiding City, that hath Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> Heb. 11.10. Heb. 13.14. from whence all Sorrow, Pain, Miſery, and Death are baniſhed for ever, and <hi>where fulneſs of joy doth dwell, and rivers of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual pleaſures do flow for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All Gods Children ſhall be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into their Fathers Houſe; all his Subjects ſhall be taken into, and ſhall dwell in the Kings Palace: And Gods Palace is not like the Great <hi>Turk's</hi> Seraglio
<note n="*" place="margin">Turkiſh <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragl at the end of</hi> Tavernier<hi>'s Travels.</hi>
               </note>, which one ingeniouſly calls a Paradiſe for one,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:54706:60"/>but a Priſon to all others that reſide in it. But this Royal Manſion of the King of Glory is not only a Paradiſe to Chriſt, but to all his Members; they enjoy the Riches, partake of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and taſte the Pleaſures of it: Let Faith paſs within the Walls, and walk in the Streets of this heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> O! ſtrive by a Spiritual Eye to ſee the true King <hi>Solomon</hi> wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Glittering and Glorious Crown: though men hid their Faces from him (as a Leper) trod on him as a Worm, deſpiſed and abbhored him, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 49.7. yet he was glorious in the Eyes of the Lord, God the Father received him into Heaven, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed him thither with theſe Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Words, <hi>Sit thou on my Right Hand till I make all thy Foes to be thy Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool,</hi> Pſ. 110.1. And as Chriſt was treated after his Sufferings, ſo will he entertain his People after their Sorrows and Afflictions: How wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come will they be to him, when they come out of the Field, and arrive from off a Stormy and Raging Sea? how will he chear and comfort them?
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:54706:61"/>How kindly will he ſpeak to them? What marks of Honour will he put upon them? How will he praiſe their Faith, commend their Love, approve and applaud their Conſtancy and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to him? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. How ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably doth Chriſt ſpeak of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas, Rev.</hi> 2.13. He Styles him <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas his Faithful Martyr.</hi> So Chriſt will Paint out the Services and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of his People before his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; he will acknowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs their Names thus, Theſe are they that have followed me in a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; that have walked after me in the Valley of the Shadow of Death; that have abode with me in dark hours of Temptation; that have paſſed through Fiery Tryals, and have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured great Fights of Affliction: have taken joyfully the Spoiling of their Goods; that have rejoyced they were accounted worthy to ſuffer for my Namesſake; that have not loved their Lives to the Death. How will ſuch a Confeſſion of their Names by Chriſt, put Eternal Honour on the Saints? O! look beyond this gloomy
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:54706:61"/>Valley of the Shadow of Death, to an Inheritance in Light, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12. Look beyond this ſhort Night of Sorrows and Sufferings, to the bright and glorious Morning of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 49.14. Though Saints now bow down, and are laid as the Mire of the Streets, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 51. <hi>laſt. Yet the upright ſhall have Dominion in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they ſhall tread down the Wicked, they ſhall be as Aſhes under the ſoles of their Feet,</hi> Pſ. 45.14. Mal. 2.3. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigal</hi> went forth to <hi>David</hi> in his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted State, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.4, 14, 40, 42. Married and followed him in a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs; and afterwards did partake of his Honour and Proſperity. We read, that after <hi>Sauls</hi> Death, he led her out of this Wilderneſs-ſtate, into the Royal City of <hi>Hebron,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.2. Even ſo, if you now go out to Chriſt while his People are in a Wilderneſs, Afflicted and Perſecuted in the world, Jeſus Chriſt will make you partakers of his Honour, Felicity, and Glory: The time will come when this Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual King <hi>David</hi> will lead his Afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Spouſe to his Royal City above;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:54706:62"/>will place her at his Right Hand, and delight in her as his <hi>Hephzibah</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Direct. We muſt be filled with the Spirit</hi> Eph. 5.18. As there is ſuch a ſtrong and ſwift Current that always runs in at the <hi>Straits Mouth,</hi> into the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea, that a Ship cannot come out at the <hi>Straits Mouth,</hi> if it hath not a good ſtiff Gale of Wind: So truly, there is ſuch a ſtrong Torrent of Self-love, and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Affections that runs into the Camp of this World, that a Soul can never come out to Jeſus through the Streights of Afflictions and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and croſs this violent Stream of ſinful ſelf-love, and worldly luſts, if the Sails of our Souls be not migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily filled with the Gales of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. The <hi>Hebrews,</hi> after they were enlightned, <hi>endured a great fight of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, Heb.</hi> 10.32. And who is it that doth enlighten, <hi>but the Spirit of Wiſdom and Revelation?</hi> Eph. 1.17.18. Our ſight is cleared and recovered by the Spirits Eye-Salve, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.18. ſo that we can ſee more, and further than the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:54706:62"/>reſt of the World: Hence Saints are called <hi>Children of Light,</hi> Luke 16.8. becauſe they look into, and take hold of another world: As <hi>Stephens</hi> Eye was extraordinarily fortified and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, <hi>that he could ſee up into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and behold Jeſus at the Right Hand of God,</hi> Acts 7.55, 56. So the Spirit doth ſo renew and enlighten the Eyes of Saints Minds, that they can ſee In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, Heavenly and Eternal things: And it is this ſight that eſtabliſhes the Heart againſt the threatnings and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the World: <hi>That which is born of the Spirit, is Spirit,</hi> John 3.6. that is, <hi>Such are Spiritual Creatures, and are alſo called Heavenly,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.48. If you are Spirit, you will not luſt after and be captivated by Carnal things: If you are heavenly Creatures, you will not ſtoop and bow down to this Earth for your Happineſs: <hi>It is by the Spirit that we muſt mortifie the Deeds of the Body, and Members upon Earth,</hi> Rom. 8.13. Col. 3.5. Theſe luſts that are fixed on, fed and filled by Objects on Earth, are tempting and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down Souls to a Center and Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:54706:63"/>here below; and it is by the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Spirit only, that we can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and ſubdue them: The Apoſtle bids <hi>Timothy to partake of the Afflictions of the Goſpel, according to the Power of God,</hi> 2. Tim. 1.8. If we are to bear them our ſelves, and were left to the frailty of Nature, how ſoon ſhould we be foiled and overcome? But Saints, by the Spirit and its power, are ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to deny themſelves, to conquer the Fleſh, and tread the world under their Feet. Chriſt hath promiſed <hi>not to leave his People comfortleſs,</hi> John 14.16, 18. <hi>but that he would ſend them the Comforter:</hi> What the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhews,
<note place="margin">John 16.13.8. Rom. 16.17. Eph. 1.13.</note> teſtifies, ſeals to the Souls of Believers, is ſufficient to buoy up the Hearts of Chriſtians a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Temporal Evils: If the Spirit could make ſupply inſtead of Chriſts Bodily Preſence with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; if it could chear them in the abſence, and withdrawing of Chriſts Humane Nature; can it not much more comfort us in the abſence or loſs of outward Enjoyments? As a Tree that
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:54706:63"/>hath a River at its Root, can retain its Verdure and Flouriſhing Sate, though there be a great Drought, and no Showers come upon it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.8. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 5.2. So if we have the Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter within, if we are watered by the Rivers of its Conſolations, may we not be ſatisfied from our ſelves, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.14. though we have no Showers of worldly comforts or enjoyments? If men would ſtir, and labour, and thereby excite their Natural Heat, they would not abſolutely need Fire in the coldeſt Weather to warm them. So if Chriſtians did more ſtir up Faith, <hi>and walk in the Comfort of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Acts 9.31. they would little need or regard the worlds conſolations: If you be led by the Spirit of Chriſt, it will in ſome meaſure work in you, as in him; it will raiſe in you ſuch apprehenſions, and kindle in you ſuch Affections as were found in Jeſus. <hi>He that is joyned to the Lord is one Spirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.17. That is, He is of the ſame Spirit, of the ſame Temper, of the ſame Diſpoſition and Inclinations with Jeſus Chriſt: As if the ſame Soul did animate many Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:54706:64"/>theſe ſeveral Perſons would be of the ſame Will, and have the ſame Affections: So the Spirit of Chriſt dwelling in his People, the ſame will be in them as was found in Jeſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5. O! how freely did Jeſus Chriſt yield himſelf to ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and death? Pſ. 40.7, 8. <hi>Lo, I come, I delight to do thy will, O God; yea thy Law is within my Heart.</hi> And what was the Will of God, that Jeſus Chriſt did delight to do? We are told what this Will was, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.10. <hi>viz. that Jeſus Chriſt ſhould offer his Body once for all!</hi> How difficult and hard was this Service? yet ſuch a Law of Love to the Father and periſhing ſinners was written in the Heart of Chriſt, <hi>that he was ſtraitned till this Bloody Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm was fulfilled,</hi> Luke 12.50. Though his Cup of Sufferings was ſo deep, ſo large, tempered with ſo many bitter Ingredients, yet he reſigned himſelf, and ſaid, <hi>Father, if this Cup may not paſs except I drink of it, thy Will be done.</hi> Matt. 26.42. When <hi>Peter</hi> tempted him to favour, ſpare, and indulge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he ſharply rebuked him, and ſaid,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:54706:64"/>
               <hi>Get thou behind me Satan, thou art an offence to me,</hi> Matt. 16.22, 23. How did Chriſt deny himſelf, and ſubject his Will to the Will of God? And when Chriſt was raiſed from the Dead, how did he deſpiſe and diſdain to be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſtay here below by the beſt things of this World? Would the Riches, Honours, Pleaſures, of this world then have allured the Eye, cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated or chained the Heart of Chriſt here below? Could ſuch things ſtay or ſtop, detain or ſix him here below? Was he not exceedingly raiſed in his Mind and Affections, above the beſt things of this world? This was his Requeſt and Prayer to the Father, <hi>Now glorifie me with thy own ſelf, with the glory that I had with thee before the Foundations of the World,</hi> John 17.5. His Mind did ſoar upwards; his Heart did aſpire to a heavenly Kingdom and Glory. Now if this Spirit of the Lord Jeſus do dwell in our Hearts, will it not fix our hearts, and fortifie our reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to go through Fire and Water, Floods and Storms, for the Honour of God, and for the Glory of Chriſt? Shall
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:54706:65"/>we be of timerous, baſe, daſtardly Spirits, if the bleſſed Spirit of Jeſus do dwell in us? And ſhall we not ſlight alſo and contemn, turn our Eyes from, and our Backs upon all the Beauty and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of this world, if the Spirit hath given us a ſight of the Glory of God in the Face of Chriſt? Shall we not cry out to God, as the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73.25, 26. <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee? and there is none on Earth that I deſire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thee.</hi> How will ſuch a Soul rate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and rebuke tempting Objects, and ſay, Get you gone, I have fatneſs and ſweetneſs; I have fulneſs and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in my Lord Jeſus; my Eyes are clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt your Beauty, my Ears are ſtopt againſt your Charms: Chriſt I have choſen, and I ſee no cauſe to repent of my choice; to him therefore will I cleave and ſtick for ever? And that you may obtain this bleſſed Spirit, and all Spiritual good things, as flowing from him; Bow your Knees to the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>And if Parents that are evil, do yet know how to give good gifts to their Children, much more ſhall our heavenly Father give the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to them that ask him,</hi> Luke 11.13.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:54706:65"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
